<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>mort’s mythopœia - reviewing</title>
    <subtitle>with apologies</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://mort.io/tags/reviewing/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2024-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mort.io/tags/reviewing/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Post-COVID19 TPC experience</title>
        <published>2024-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/post-covid-tpc/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/post-covid-tpc/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/post-covid-tpc/">&lt;p&gt;I do not participate in a huge number of TPCs (Technical Programme Committees)
as a general rule– partly time constraints but mostly no-one knows who I am so
I don’t often get asked… (!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have done a few though, some big (e.g., &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usenix.org&#x2F;conference&#x2F;nsdi15&quot;&gt;USENIX NSDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;conferences.sigcomm.org&#x2F;imc&#x2F;2018&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ACM IMC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;),
some small (&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;uksystems.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;UK Systems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;link.springer.com&#x2F;conference&#x2F;pam&quot;&gt;PAM&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), and perhaps because I only do
a couple every few years, while doing &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;conferences2.sigcomm.org&#x2F;co-next&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ACM
CoNEXT&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;acm-ieee-sec.org&#x2F;list&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ACM&#x2F;IEEE
SEC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; this week, I found myself particularly
noticing some changes in practice since that last TPCs I recall (notably
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usenix.org&#x2F;conference&#x2F;nsdi15&quot;&gt;NSDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;conferences.sigcomm.org&#x2F;imc&#x2F;2018&#x2F;&quot;&gt;IMC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). So here are three observations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-online-first-and-only&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#1-online-first-and-only&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: 1-online-first-and-only&quot;&gt;1. Online, first and only&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest obvious change is that TPC meetings are now online rather than
in-person. This has one big disadvantage for me: I really enjoyed travelling to
the meeting to meet colleagues and (usually) participate in some TPC-oriented
workshop with presentations of recent an in-progress work. In many ways, I found
this sort of activity more interesting than the conference itself (sorry!). It
also has the unfortunate effect that, at least for international TPCs, timezones
make scheduling tricky – one benefit of travelling was that at least the
meeting took place in localtime for (almost) everyone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it also has clear benefits: the CO2 footprint of the event is
dramatically reduced which can only be a good thing. The financial cost
reduction probably also opens up the experience to attendees who would never
previously have been able to make it. I’ve rarely seen really poor meeting
behaviour on the TPCs I’ve been involved in, but I also find that in an online
meeting, chairing tends to be more easily more rigorous and the sometimes
dominating effect of a single confident (perhaps I might say over-confident, or
even just loud) individual is significantly reduced. Which is good.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-offline-dominance&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#2-offline-dominance&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: 2-offline-dominance&quot;&gt;2. Offline dominance&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now see &lt;strong&gt;dramatically&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; more use being made of commenting and discussions in
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;read.seas.harvard.edu&#x2F;~kohler&#x2F;hotcrp&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HotCRP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which remains the only
conference management and paper reviewing platform I will willingly use (thanks
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Eddie_Kohler&quot;&gt;Eddie&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;!). I don’t know whether this
is a post-pandemic effect, or just the fact that the old old guard has largely
shuffled out of active TPC duties and we now have a new old guard (ie., people
of my era) and younger who are perhaps happier to communicate and express views
without needing to be in the same room.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is another dramatic improvement in process, and puts us in a
similar place to how, for example, we handled marking final year undergraduate
projects at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.nottingham.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Nottingham University&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It means
that discussion is recorded, and usually more coherently and explicitly argued
due to the need to write it down.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-reduction-in-extremism&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#3-reduction-in-extremism&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: 3-reduction-in-extremism&quot;&gt;3. Reduction in extremism&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one arguably slightly negative comment I would have is – and this is only
my anecdotal impression, and not something I can pretend to have data on – that
I think I see a tendency for reviewers to perhaps be a little less clear in
their scoring. Once the across the board strong rejects (a fair number) and
strong accepts (a much smaller number) were taken out, I saw an awful lot of
weak reject (but happy to consider weak accept after discussion) and weak accept
(but happy to consider weak reject after discussion). This made it quite hard
for me, as another reviewer, sometimes to get a clear signal as to what the
other reviews were recommending.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a challenge I sometimes see in admissions interviewing: less experienced
interviewers are sometimes  reluctant to give a clear signal, exhibiting instead
a tendency to score near or perhaps just above the middle of the scale. (I
remember doing this myself.) This feels more comfortable – putting one’s head
above the parapet by taking a clear stance often feels more socially awkward
than giving a “fine, ok, pretty good, sure” response, not least because it needs
stronger supporting argument – but in the end I think it misses the point of
being an interviewer &#x2F; a TPC member which is exactly to accept or reject papers
based on having been recognised for your expertise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the end, two good points, two potential (but minor) negatives, and one
completely unjustifiable and purely selfish negative. Which on the whole is a
good thing. Though having come back to this after a break for a couple of years,
I find I am even more sceptical of the whole process than I was. More later
perhaps, once I get my thoughts in order.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
