<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>mort’s mythopœia - random</title>
    <subtitle>with apologies</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://mort.io/tags/random/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2024-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mort.io/tags/random/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Workshopping, across the universe</title>
        <published>2024-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/">&lt;p&gt;One of the pleasures of being an academic is to travel to nice places to meet
interesting people, and interesting places to meet nice people. In one of my
first such trips for a few years I recently went to Sweden to participate in the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;17th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;17th Cloud Control Workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;17th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;photo.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of the presenter in front of a slide&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d previously attended the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;15th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;15th Cloud Control
Workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; shortly before the pandemic
happened, causing the series to pause briefly. This was the reboot, and as
before, it was a great deal of fun: good company, good food, beautiful location.
If you get the chance to go, take it if you can!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop is a really nice mix of keynote presentations – not too many and
not too long at 20 minutes (mostly) – and discussion sessions proposed
beforehand or on site by participants. I gave one of the keynotes, talking about
the challenges posed and opportunities offered by edge computing. Can share
slides on request, or when I decide on a good way to publish them!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also enjoyed many good discussions and conversations, topped off with a great
BBQ, but two topics stand out. First, a great discussion session organised by
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;anakli.inf.ethz.ch&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Prof. Ana Klimović&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; about serverless computing
which immediately triggered some thoughts about possible followup publications
from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edgeless-project.eu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EDGELESS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and collaboration possibilities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, several conversations on a topic I know little about, low-earth orbit
(LEO) satellite networking, and what could be done with it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, my thought was whether a LEO constellation plus a little
edge compute could provide a difficult-to-disrupt out-of-band monitoring network
for critical infrastructure like datacenters and power grids: although data
bandwidth is limited and a bit complicated due to the constraints on ground
stations, they have pretty decent cameras, so why not use those to capture and
locally process images of the roofs of large rectangular buildings like
datacenters and the like which could continually display various status data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such status information would only need to be locally generated, so it would
take fairly substantial physical disruption of the facility (also presumably
noticeable by camera) to prevent that working. Alternatively, the constellation
(perhaps shared across multiple facilities in different jurisdictions) would
need to be substantially disrupted to prevent it being able to monitor targets.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a fun discussion anyway, combining a network technology I knew little
about with possibly interesting applications of edge computing to resiliency.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Postcript: in case you’re curious, the title is a passing reference to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Star_Trekkin%27&quot;&gt;Star
Trekkin’&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a fine popular music
single from my youth. Which has a much longer back-story on Wikipedia than I had
anticipated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
