<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>mort’s mythopœia - academic</title>
      <link>https://mort.io</link>
      <description>with apologies</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://mort.io/tags/academic/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 18</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w18/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w18/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w18/">&lt;p&gt;So. That was a rather stop-start week.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It started off pretty well: as &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;sabbatical-diary-w16-17&#x2F;&quot;&gt;noted last
week&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I was in Brussels to attend &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fosdem.org&#x2F;2026&#x2F;&quot;&gt;FOSDEM
2026&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for the first time in a decade. As well as
getting my tax return submitted to HMRC before the deadline on the Saturday, I
also managed to finish my slides—more precisely, editing Amjad’s slides—to
give my talk on Sunday literally &lt;em&gt;hours&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-hours-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-hours&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; beforehand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;video.fosdem.org&#x2F;2026&#x2F;ua2114&#x2F;F33P7S-unlocking_extra_cluster_capacity_with_enhanced_linux_cgroup_scheduling.av1.webm&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;talk-title.webp&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;Splash slide for a FOSDEM 2026 talk title _Unlocking extra cluster
        capacity with enhanced Linux cgroup scheduling&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;neilzone.co.uk&#x2F;2026&#x2F;02&#x2F;reflections-on-my-first-day-ever-at-fosdem&#x2F;&quot;&gt;as others have
commented&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
it was very busy, and the venue quality was a bit patchy: some rooms seemed to
work really well, some were rather hot with lots of background noise. It was
great to catch up with a few folk though, as well as to give &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;video.fosdem.org&#x2F;2026&#x2F;ua2114&#x2F;F33P7S-unlocking_extra_cluster_capacity_with_enhanced_linux_cgroup_scheduling.av1.webm&quot;&gt;Amjad’s talk,
“Unlocking extra cluster capacity with enhanced Linux cgroup
scheduling”&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Got a couple of good questions, plus a couple more
follow-up chats off-mic. All-in-all I was pretty pleased with the attendance
given it was the graveyard shift as the last talk in the Kernel devroom before
the closing conference keynote in another building. For those who want more than
the video, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mort.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;sabbatical-diary-w18&#x2F;.&#x2F;fosdem26-mortier.pdf&quot;&gt;find the slides here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I even managed to make it to the station on time notwithstanding having to bail
off the tram and walk a bit to the metro due to police cars blocking the way,
and then putting up with the usual rather stringent approach Brussels Eurostar
seems to take to gate closing times.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-eurostar-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-eurostar&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; So that was nice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately most of the rest of the week after I got back was taken up with a
meeting for some external work I do (fun!) followed by a stomach bug for ~36
hours (not fun!). And then recovery, both physical and catching up on the
resulting backlog.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ho hum. Hopefully next week will be better! Or at least less… runny.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-hours&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least one. Maybe as much as two. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-hours-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-eurostar&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously. Why does Brussels seem to be so much more rigid about
this. I never have a problem at stations in London, Paris,
Amsterdam. But for some reason, Brussels seems to close the gate
absolutely on the dot of 30min before the train, no matter what. In
this case I arrived to an almost empty hall—about three other
people going through security ahead of me—to “are you for the
18.52?” “yes” “you have one minute before the gate closes”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-eurostar-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Weeks 16&#x2F;17 &#x2F; Months 2---4</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w16-17/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w16-17/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w16-17/">&lt;p&gt;More personal and suchlike stuff going on the last two weeks, hence the week’s
gap. Felt less productive as a result, though some things got done I guess.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I engaged with a range of students:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some Ph.D. supervising of my newest student, Yaman Kalaji (more later)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;helped out the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.srcf.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;SRCF&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for which I appear to have
become Senior Treasurer&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;did some more Ph.D. and M.Phil. assessment and interviewing&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started wrapping up the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edgeless-project.eu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EDGELESS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; project in
the sense of getting the no-cost extension sorted out, signing off on the
(almost) final timesheets, and other exciting administrative tasks. I also think
I’ve unblocked (finally!) the industrial funding project proposal &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;sabbatical-diary-w11-12&#x2F;&quot;&gt;I’ve
mentioned previously&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I participated in a visit by a Ukrainian Teachers’ association, answering
questions about Christ’s and Computer Science.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished the review process for EuroSys 2026—just one of my batch of five
from this round accepted (but I think 20% is about usual for EuroSys).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I circulated and got initial feedback from several people on the &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;sabbatical-diary-w6-9&#x2F;&quot;&gt;writing
previously mentioned&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in which I try to give an
overview of how undergraduate education works at the University. Feedback was
both less bad than I’d feared and more useful than I’d hoped (!) in that I
didn’t think it was close to being ready for detailed feedback, but apparently
it was. Though it’s already eight pages and counting; looks like it’ll be about
ten by the time it’s done.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also fed into a consultation about end-to-end encryption and law enforcement
activity, largely repeating many of the things &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;cosi-lawful-access&#x2F;&quot;&gt;said to the COSI
meeting&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which was an interesting chat.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I even did some Actual Science™ by walking the William Gates Building to
validate that the building management system’s temperature sensors really were
behaving themselves as we’d spotted room temperatures ranging from 12—25°C
on a cold day a couple of weeks ago, which seemed rather a wide range. But they
did seem to be. Possibly more evidence that sorting the heating out really could
have some useful impact on energy consumption (and thus both bills and carbon
output).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…And finally! Earlier today I travelled to lovely Brussels to attend &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fosdem.org&#x2F;2026&#x2F;&quot;&gt;FOSDEM
2026&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for the first time in a decade. Due to visa
issues it looks like I’ll be presenting Amjad’s work&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-visa-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-visa&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; on Sunday—maybe
see you there :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-visa&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second time this happened, the first being the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sesame23.github.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;SESAME
2023&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3592533.3592807&quot;&gt;paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in Rome. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-visa-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Some Remarks on the Risks of Lawful Access</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/cosi-lawful-access/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/cosi-lawful-access/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/cosi-lawful-access/">&lt;p&gt;Last summer I was invited to participate in an informal meeting of the EU
Standing Committee on Operational Cooperation on Internal Security (COSI). The
session I was asked to join concerned end-to-end encryption (“E2EE”). I was
asked to “…set the scene for the discussion laying out in layman’s terms the
technical possibilities of access to data and the technical consequences of it”,
before being followed by the two other organizations presenting.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-chatham-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-chatham&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I present below the remarks I made. Unusually for me, I actually wrote down all
the words I intended to say in advance rather than using slides and winging it
in the usual way. The context and topic felt like it would be worth avoiding
slips of the tongue in this case. I gave it pretty much as written—even when I
try, I can’t help a small amount of ad libbing! But I did not deviate
significantly from this text.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having sought feedback from others on this, I would like to add a couple of
remarks as a preface.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the “Police Behaving Badly” paper puts the percentage of cybercrime
convictions involving police at 56% in the first half of 2024, and details how
police have had encrypted communication data but had it leaked by a corrupt
intelligence analyst advising her drug dealer friend that it was compromised.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, although I did try to be clear, I could have been more explicit that a
significant challenge in this space is the inevitability of software bugs.
(Approximately) All software contains bugs and it is almost certain that any
exceptional access system, due to the unavoidable complexity of such systems,
will contain bugs and so will not work as intended. The position I am trying to
take is that, while that is insufficient reason to reject every such proposal,
it is important to be realistic about the risks so that the costs and benefits
can be weighed rationally.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#who-am-i&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who am I?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I should introduce myself. I am Richard Mortier, more commonly known as
Mort. I am a professor in the Department of Computer Science &amp;amp; Technology at
Cambridge University, UK, and Fellow of Christ’s College, Cambridge. I
previously spent 6 years as a researcher with Microsoft Research Cambridge,
and 6 months with Sprint Advanced Technology Labs, California, and I have
founded three startups. I am currently also a member of the UK’s Investigatory
Powers’ Commissioner’s Office Technology Advisory Panel.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primary expertise is in computer systems and networking, and human-computer
interaction. I thus speak on this topic as a computer scientist with general
expertise in computer systems rather than as a specialist in encryption or
messaging systems. I make these remarks in a personal capacity, representing
no-one’s views but my own.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-debate&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#this-debate&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: this-debate&quot;&gt;This debate&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been asked to speak to you today about &lt;strong&gt;lawful&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;exceptional
access&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. I will stay above the nitty-gritty technical details of encryption,
communications protocols and so on, while still staying sufficiently grounded
in technology that this is not a purely abstract, philosophical debate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My impression of this debate is that it can often descend into an unhelpful
back and forth between two extreme positions that I might simplistically
characterize as “We must provide lawful access—think of the children!” and
“We cannot provide lawful access—privacy is a fundamental right!”. “We
must!” “We can’t!” and so on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-position&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#my-position&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: my-position&quot;&gt;My position&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish to re-frame this debate to place those positions at the two extremes of
what is actually a spectrum of possibilities ranging from one where we have
mechanisms to provide perfectly secure, invisible communication among group
members where groups can form and dissolve on an ad hoc basis, to one where no
communication is possible without authorized bodies having full access to all
communication content and metadata.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither extreme is sensible or achievable in my view—but intermediate
positions might be. The basis for a society to decide where it wants to be on
that spectrum requires articulation and evaluation of the risks involved. I
observe, as a computer scientist, that building any large-scale
network-connected secure system is complex, and all complexity has costs and
introduces risks. Typically, the more complex, the more cost and the more
risk. Implementation of lawful access mechanisms is inevitably complex as they
are powerful and must be secured against external and internal bad actors.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This needs to be acknowledged in the discussion. These are not trivial
mechanisms and may even involve research activity in order to articulate the
design space and understand the trade-offs involved. Justification for these
mechanisms thus needs to be stronger than “we once had this ability, so we are
worried about losing it”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;relevant-terms&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#relevant-terms&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: relevant-terms&quot;&gt;Relevant terms&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will define some relevant terms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encryption&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; refers to the transformation of &lt;em&gt;plain text&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; information into a
&lt;em&gt;cipher text&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; such that only the authorized parties can decrypt the cipher
text, transforming it back into the plain text. Such transformations are
usually described in mathematical terms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;encryption scheme&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is a scheme for exchanging secret data over an
insecure channel using encryption. As they are based on mathematical
operations, it is generally possible to give guarantees about how
computationally difficult it is to, for example, work out the plain text that
produced a given cipher text—that is, to break the encryption scheme.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many such schemes with a range of trade-offs between complexity,
computational cost, and how difficult they make it for an unauthorized party
to decrypt a cipher text. All rely at some level on the creation and
consumption of secret &lt;strong&gt;key material&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to perform transformations between
plain text and cipher text.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, an encryption scheme has to be reduced to an implementation,
usually in software. It takes considerable effort to ensure that a given
implementation correctly implements the encryption scheme, and even more
effort to ensure that it does not leak information about the plain text
message or the secret key material during encryption or (attempted)
decryption.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secure messaging systems&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; are Internet-connected services that provide for
exchange of messages between two or more individual devices. Older systems
provide message exchange by having devices send messages to central servers
that then replicate those messages, transmitting them to other devices
participating in the conversation. This requires those central servers to have
access to the secret key material so that they can decrypt messages to work
out where to send them on to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End-to-end encryption&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; refers to those encryption systems where this is not
the case: the central servers that assist in replication of messages to the
intended recipients do not have access to the secret key material and so
cannot decrypt the encrypted messages. Only the participating devices can do
that. End-to-end encryption is increasingly common in consumer-grade messaging
applications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;lawful&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (or &lt;strong&gt;exceptional&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;) &lt;strong&gt;access&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in this context refers to
technical mechanisms provided to enable authorized bodies such as law
enforcement and intelligence services to access communications systems on
production of suitable authorization. In the UK, for example, this would
entail the relevant body seeking a suitable warrant under the Investigatory
Powers Act (2016) as amended. Lawful access mechanisms have historically been
provided in many communication systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-problem&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End-to-end encryption does make provision of lawful access more difficult: the
secret key material is in principle never held by the service provider and so
they cannot simply grant access to messages. Mechanisms would need to be added
to enable such access. But as soon as any mechanism exists for a third party
to gain access to decrypted messages, bad actors will also seek to exploit it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such mechanisms are powerful, as with any additional feature they add
complexity and increase the likelihood of creating vulnerabilities that can be
attacked. And so the argument goes that we &lt;strong&gt;cannot&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; provide lawful access
mechanisms because it would be irresponsible to do so, weakening protections
that law-abiding members of society rely upon for so many different purposes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, so the counter-argument continues, lawful access is necessary to protect
the public including the vulnerable and children. Bad actors make use of
secure messaging services to exchange illegal material, to plan and execute
serious crimes, to commit terrorism and so forth. So mechanisms for lawful
access &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; be provided otherwise it is impossible for law enforcement to
carry out their duties to enforce the law and protect society. And so the
argument continues that we must provide mechanisms for lawful access.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t. We must. We can’t. We must. Both positions are extreme points in a
spectrum of risk. What I believe we can and must do is take a risk-based
approach to this challenge: articulate the risks and, if we decide they are
worth taking, develop mechanisms to mitigate them. Lawful access can be done
and has been done—but should it be done, and how?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;two-principles&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#two-principles&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: two-principles&quot;&gt;Two principles&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what are the principles to consider, what risks do such mechanisms create,
and how might we consider them?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first principle is that any lawful access mechanism is, by definition,
powerful. It allows an authorized party to access information that people wish
to keep secret. It is not therefore something that is easy to design,
implement, test, maintain and operate: considerable care will be required, and
potentially considerable expense incurred.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is that any such mechanism can and will be abused. Bad actors will
seek to exploit it to gain access to information, and may well succeed from
time to time. Those unauthorized accesses will come from external bad actors
but also internal bad actors. As well as the maintenance costs this creates,
it also suggests that accountability and transparency are critical.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;~ah793&#x2F;cccd.html&quot;&gt;Cambridge Computer Crime
Database&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a database of
cybercrime events of many kinds where the offender or alleged offender has
been arrested, charged and&#x2F;or prosecuted in the UK, dating from 1 January
2010. In the last 6 months of 2023, nearly half of the cases involved police
as offenders. I am not saying that these directly involve lawful access or
similar mechanisms, or that such incidents are commonplace—but it is
undeniable that they do occur, and that lawful access mechanisms could create
another route by which they can be carried out. Bad actors will also be
present in the service providers. Strong powers require strong oversight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate cannot continue under the assumptions that this is a
straightforward technology to build and protect against unauthorized use, and
that authorized users will always use it lawfully.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;thinking-about-risk-necessity-proportionality&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#thinking-about-risk-necessity-proportionality&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: thinking-about-risk-necessity-proportionality&quot;&gt;Thinking about risk: necessity &amp;amp; proportionality&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is useful to think about the risks from a perspective of necessity
and proportionality.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;strong&gt;necessity&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: what is it that lawful access enables, and why?
Mechanisms could be built to enable a range of types of lawful access. For
example, access to the content of all messages; access to the content of all
messages involving certain keywords or with attached images that trigger some
flag; access to the content of all messages involving certain participants;
access to the content of selected messages; or access to metadata about
messages such as participant identifiers, message timestamps, locations of
transmission and reception, whether for all messages, all messages involving
certain parties, or specific messages. To determine what access is appropriate
requires articulating the purpose: to what use will the information be put? By
whom? And are there really no existing mechanisms by which the desired outcome
can be achieved?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;strong&gt;proportionality&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: what are the effects of exercising lawful access,
and how are the harms to be balanced against the benefits? All the mechanisms
listed above create risks when abused—but some create more risks than
others. Creating an ability, however well protected, to read any and all
messages between any communicating parties clearly creates enormous potential
for privacy infringement and crime. Creating an ability simply to know which
accounts communicated and when also creates risks but perhaps lesser ones in
most cases.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These perspectives need to be tested and debated before suitable mechanisms
can be designed, implemented, and exercised. Oversight mechanisms—perhaps
including by non-governmental organizations—need to be part of the design.
The intended benefits need to be articulated. Usage and impact need to be
tracked. Scope creep and the ability to silently expand the reach of such a
capability to enable mass surveillance needs to be guarded against. Comparison
needs to be made against alternative current approaches. For example, a
warrant can be obtained to hack a target’s phone giving access to all content
on that device, not just their messages; is that more or less intrusive than
providing a mechanism that enables selected messages or communications’
metadata to be obtained on presentation of a suitable warrant, but which
simply cannot be used to reveal any other content?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world where, as I understand it, policing resources are constantly being
stretched, how will law enforcement ensure it has the capacity to use
effectively information gained via such lawful access mechanisms? The risks
created by these mechanisms, once deployed, are always present even when they
are not being legally exercised: creating the mechanisms and then not
effectively using them considerably reduces any proportionality argument. If
the resource to sift existing data is already stretched, how will putting more
hay on the haystack help in finding the needles?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the success of operations against systems such as
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;EncroChat&quot;&gt;Encrochat&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.bbc.co.uk&#x2F;news&#x2F;articles&#x2F;clyljpygxgjo&quot;&gt;Ghost&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; raises the question:
is it enough to concentrate on those systems that target criminal use? How
much extra will be gained by creating lawful access mechanisms in
consumer-grade systems? I am not saying nothing will be gained—but the
expected benefits need to be quantified for the case to be made.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the call for lawful access mechanisms based on specific, recorded instances
where they would have made a material difference to society? Or is it based
primarily on fear of a future where once useful mechanisms cease to be
available? “Once we could but now we cannot” is not a very strong argument for
necessity and proportionality given the way that technology has constantly
evolved over decades and centuries.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Communications_Assistance_for_Law_Enforcement_Act&quot;&gt;Communications Assistance for Law Enforcement Act (CALEA)
1994&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
enforced US communications providers to implement wire-tapping capabilities.
It also mandated that those providers secure their networks. Unfortunately, it
seems that the implementation of &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.schneier.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;archives&#x2F;2025&#x2F;04&#x2F;arguing-against-calea.html&quot;&gt;that capability created a risk that was
exploited&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
by a group dubbed &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;techcrunch.com&#x2F;2024&#x2F;10&#x2F;07&#x2F;the-30-year-old-internet-backdoor-law-that-came-back-to-bite&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Salt
Typhoon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
to allow capture of sensitive call metadata in Washington D.C. Experts have
been reported as saying that such an attack was “inevitable”. How can such
risks, in terms of both likelihood and impact, be quantified and weighed in
the balance?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-solutions&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#non-solutions&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: non-solutions&quot;&gt;Non-solutions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth at this point dismissing some ways that have in the past been
proposed for lawful access but which have very significant problems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, deliberately weakening encryption schemes. This simply does not work in
practice: bad actors will use more secure schemes anyway, and will seek to
exploit law-abiding services that use the weakened schemes, putting
law-abiding users at risk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, forms of key escrow. This is where the secret key material is placed
under the control of some trusted party, and can be accessed on presentation
of a suitably authorized request. Unfortunately, this allows anyone who can
produce, whether or not legitimately, such a request to access &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;
communications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, ghost users. This is where providers add law enforcement operatives to
chats without triggering notifications or otherwise informing chat
participants that a new member has been added. While in some ways technically
attractive, as described such a mechanism provides no means for accountability
and oversight: what record is made, and how is it inspected, that such an
action was carried out by the service provider, for what purpose, at what
time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-possible-solution&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#a-possible-solution&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: a-possible-solution&quot;&gt;A possible solution&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will close by sketching &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;martin.kleppmann.com&#x2F;2021&#x2F;07&#x2F;16&#x2F;cryptographic-backdoors-hotpets.html&quot;&gt;a proposal from a colleague, Dr Martin
Kleppmann&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
for a lawful access mechanism that seeks to balance benefits and harms,
published at the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;petsymposium.org&#x2F;2021&#x2F;hotpets.php&quot;&gt;HotPETS (Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium) Workshop
in 2021&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It seeks to ensure that
undetectable mass surveillance cannot be carried out, and that oversight can
be exercised in relevant jurisdictions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, it provides a public &lt;em&gt;transparency log&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; into which all accepted
lawful access requests are written with a few publicly readable fields
indicating the requesting body, the warrant jurisdiction, its basis and
validity period, plus some cryptographic commitment as to the target for the
warrant. Thus, anyone can see how many warrants are being issued, why, and
when &lt;em&gt;without the targets being revealed&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service’s client application then checks the log and if it finds a valid
entry for the device it is running on, it uploads the requested data for the
indicated period to the specified LEA. This is similar to the message backup
procedure already provided for by many secure messaging applications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, a trusted oversight body in the jurisdiction can cross-check
log entries against issued warrants, and require the service provider to
reveal the targets of those warrants so that proportionality can be justified
by reference to the seriousness of the crime of which they are accused.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provides targeted upload of data, reducing the ease with which bad actors
can use it to acquire data themselves. It enables interested parties, perhaps
including civil society organizations, to monitor general use of the mechanism
so that moves towards mass surveillance can be detected. It enables trusted
oversight bodies to exercise powers to inspect and ensure that necessity and
proportionality requirements are being met.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a fully worked up proposal, and it does not thoroughly address
every possible challenge. To produce such a proposal would require, as well as
some of the discussion and debate referred to above, more technical details
about how the communications services that would be subject to such mechanisms
are architected and operated. But it hopefully serves as an example of an
approach that sits on the spectrum somewhere between “We can’t” and “We must”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#conclusions&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary then,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe that it is in principle possible to design, implement and deploy
lawful access mechanisms, even in end-to-end encrypted systems.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But doing so requires careful justification as to necessity and
proportionality: just because such mechanisms could be built and would be
useful does not automatically mean that they should be built.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Such justification must include realistic consideration of the risks even
just the existence of such mechanisms would introduce, as well as
mechanisms to mitigate those risks.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To maintain public trust in secure communications means that such strong
powers must be designed and implemented so as to enable strong oversight
by trusted bodies, likely including non-governmental bodies.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#references&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: references&quot;&gt;References&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.lawfaremedia.org&#x2F;article&#x2F;principles-more-informed-exceptional-access-debate&quot;&gt;Principles for a More Informed Exceptional Access Debate&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”,
Ian Levy &amp;amp; Crispin Robinson. 29 November 2018.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;~ah793&#x2F;papers&#x2F;2019inside_out.pdf&quot;&gt;Inside out: Characterising cybercrimes committed inside and outside the
workplace&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”.
Alice Hutchings and Ben Collier, Cambridge University. IEEE European
Symposium on Security and Privacy Workshops (EuroS&amp;amp;PW) 2019, pp. 481– 490.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gov.uk&#x2F;government&#x2F;publications&#x2F;open-letter-to-mark-zuckerberg&#x2F;written-testimony-of-chloe-squires-director-national-security-home-office&quot;&gt;Judiciary Committee United States Senate hearing: Encryption and Lawful
Access: Evaluating Benefits and Risks to Public Safety and Privacy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”,
Chloe Squires, Director National Security, Home Office. 23 December 2019.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;securephones.io&#x2F;main.html&quot;&gt;Data Security on Mobile Devices: Current State of the Art, Open
Problems, and Proposed Solutions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”,
Maximilian Zinkus, Tushar M. Jois, Matthew Green, Johns Hopkins
University. 6 June 2021.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;martin.kleppmann.com&#x2F;papers&#x2F;backdoors-hotpets21.pdf&quot;&gt;Harm Reduction for Cryptographic
Backdoors&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”,
Martin Kleppmann, Cambridge University. 14th Workshop on Hot Topics in
Privacy Enhancing Technologies (HotPETs). 16 July 2021.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;home-affairs.ec.europa.eu&#x2F;networks&#x2F;high-level-group-hlg-access-data-effective-law-enforcement_en#recommendations&quot;&gt;Concluding report of the High-Level Group on access to data for
effective law enforcement&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”.
15 November 2024.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;~ah793&#x2F;papers&#x2F;2025police.pdf&quot;&gt;Police behaving
badly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”. Alice
Hutchings, Cambridge University. IEEE Security and Privacy, 23(1),
pp.80-82. 4 February 2025.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-chatham&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A la the Chatham House Rule, we were asked not to reveal identities
of participants or the organizations they represented. I was there
in a private capacity, giving my own views as an academic computer
scientist. You might choose to guess who might be the sorts of
organization not in COSI with a stake in this debate; I couldn’t
possibly comment. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-chatham-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 15</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w15/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w15/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w15/">&lt;p&gt;That feels like it was a relatively productive week :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I interviewed a couple of Ph.D. candidates—good luck!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I obtained a short extension to the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edgeless-project.eu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EU EDGELESS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
project to allow us to spend up the remaining funds and complete all the work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I extracted myself from Ramblr: &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;extracting-rambling&#x2F;&quot;&gt;downloaded my existing
trips&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;pramblr&quot;&gt;wrote a script to generate nice
visualisations&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;tracks&#x2F;&quot;&gt;integrated it into this
website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. More polishing to follow, of both the visualisations and the
integration, but it feels like a decent start.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally! I actually got round to writing some funding proposal-related text
for the work we’re seeking to do relating to the “Digital Plant Room” and making
existing buildings more energy efficient.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty more to do, but that feels like it wasn’t a bad week in the end.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 14</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w14/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w14/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w14/">&lt;p&gt;The calendar year started with some sysadmin work. Had to &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;eduroam-update&#x2F;&quot;&gt;get devices
reconnected to &lt;code&gt;eduroam&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Internal-CL&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; Wi-Fi
networks&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which was happily quite straightforward.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research work was primarily getting a bit more seriously started on &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;sabbatical-diary-w6-9&#x2F;&quot;&gt;unexpected
work mentioned previously&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; looking at digital
support for HVAC control—a better “Digital Plant Room” if you will.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also did some recreational coding around various family duties which was nice
:) I used to use &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;everytrail.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EveryTrail&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to record GPS tracks
while out walking. This became &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.alltrails.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;AllTrails&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and (at
the time, not used it in years) got worse and probably wanted me to start
paying. About a decade ago I switched to
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ramblr.com&#x2F;web&#x2F;main&quot;&gt;ramblr&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;—but unfortunately that has also
degraded over time, with their website setup and app bit-rotting as far as I
could tell, while also reducing the free functionality and forcing users towards
their paid service.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-enshittification-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-enshittification&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I decided the time had come to extricate myself. Due to the aforementioned
bit-rot of the &lt;em&gt;ramblr&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; app, some time ago I had found a reasonable if
comparatively basic iOS app for recording GPS tracks, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.apple.com&#x2F;us&#x2F;app&#x2F;gps-tracker-pro&#x2F;id984920064&quot;&gt;GPS-Tracker
Pro&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-stalker-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-stalker&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; but
wanted some way to display and host the tracks online nicely with photos
included. It ended up being straightforward to automatically extract the ~188
tracks from &lt;em&gt;ramblr&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, I’d already got those from Everytrails when I switched
away from it, and GPS-Tracker Pro makes it straightforward enough to share GPX
and KML tracks out to e.g., cloud storage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m now partway through a simple Python script to visualise them using
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pypi.org&#x2F;project&#x2F;gpxplotter&#x2F;&quot;&gt;GPXPlotter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pypi.org&#x2F;project&#x2F;folium&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Folium&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Much more straightofrward so far
than I thought it might be. More to follow—it turns out coding is fun and I
enjoy it, so I plan to do more… :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-enshittification&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe the cool kids are now calling this
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Enshittification&quot;&gt;enshittification&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-enshittification-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-stalker&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather worryingly, reading that page today I see that the first
rating review appears to be from someone who used it to stalk their
ex-, apparently by getting a private investigator to install it on
their phone. That’s bad. Don’t do that. I only use it to record my
own tracks, obviously. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-stalker-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Updating `eduroam`</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/eduroam-update/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/eduroam-update/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/eduroam-update/">&lt;p&gt;The University recently rolled its public certificate for
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;eduroam.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;eduroam&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the old one was dropped a couple of days
ago. So double-checking that all devices still worked resulted in some fiddling
to make it so. Twice over because the local preferred Department Wi-Fi network
is &lt;code&gt;Internal-CL&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; for which I can use the same credentials.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My phone (iOS 26) was in a weird state. First off, due to having not turned off
“iCloud Passwords &amp;amp; Keychain” it turned out to have shared the credentials I
gave to my iPad. I do not want this—we can generate our own credentials, and I
generate them per-device deliberately—so that had to be turned off:
&lt;code&gt;Settings &amp;gt; Apple Account &amp;gt; iCloud &amp;gt; Saved to iCloud ... See All &amp;gt; Passwords &amp;amp; Keychain &amp;gt; Sync this iPhone&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; = &lt;code&gt;OFF&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I could forget and then rejoin &lt;code&gt;eduroam&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; using my usual credentials worked
just fine. But I couldn’t connect at all to &lt;code&gt;Internal-CL&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;—I wasn’t even
prompted for a username&#x2F;password. Also couldn’t remove it or forget it: it
showed as a “managed network” in &lt;code&gt;Settings &amp;gt; Wi-Fi &amp;gt; Edit&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. So visited
&lt;code&gt;Settings &amp;gt; General &amp;gt; Device &amp;amp; VPN Management&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; which showed &lt;code&gt;Internal-CL&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as a
“device profile”. Removed that, and then reconnected using the usual credentials
and all was well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My laptop runs NixOS so I often have to do things like this by hand. This time,
rather than faffing with &lt;code&gt;nmtui&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; I thought I’d have a go from the command-line
as I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;wifi-password&#x2F;&quot;&gt;recently found&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;re-connecting&#x2F;&quot;&gt;it to work
well&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Building off &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;help.uis.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;service&#x2F;wifi&#x2F;connect-to-eduroam&#x2F;other-devices#server&quot;&gt;the manual instructions from
UIS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
plus &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gist.github.com&#x2F;optimista&#x2F;803bbca64ae92dacab7a37e2977f1804&quot;&gt;a relevant
gist&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, the
following seems to work:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;nmcli&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; connection add type wifi con-name &amp;#39;NAME&amp;#39; ssid &amp;#39;SSID&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;  ipv4.method auto 802-1x.eap peap 802-1x.phase2-auth mschapv2&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;  802-1x.identity &amp;#39;USERNAME&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;  802-1x.password &amp;#39;PASSWORD&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;  wifi-sec.key-mgmt wpa-eap&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…setting &lt;code&gt;NAME&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;=&lt;code&gt;SSID&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to be &lt;code&gt;eduroam&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Internal-CL&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;USERNAME&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;PASSWORD&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to be my usual network credentials.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 13</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w13/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w13/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w13/">&lt;p&gt;Nothing of note done, work-wise, for the last week or so. Hey, it was the
holidays. Which meant a lot of driving around, and I find it difficult to do
much other than think and sing along to the tunes while I’m driving.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did get a chance to watch and listen to a link my mum sent me a while ago
though to a film from the BBC series &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.bbc.co.uk&#x2F;programmes&#x2F;b00tgz5d&quot;&gt;In Their Own Words: British
Novelists&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, linked from
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.openculture.com&#x2F;2012&#x2F;01&#x2F;jrr_tolkien_in_his_own_words.html&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.openculture.com&#x2F;2012&#x2F;01&#x2F;jrr_tolkien_in_his_own_words.html&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. As it
was Tolkien’s anniversary yesterday (he was born 3 January 1892), it seemed an
appropriate moment to link it here.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-title-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-title&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following quote from the man particularly resonated:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well it is meant to be escapist. Because I use escapism in its proper sense,
as of a man getting out of prison.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;J.R.R. Tolkien&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also enjoyed the distinction drawn between &lt;em&gt;allegory&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;application&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;,
noting that Shakespeare is mostly application rather than allegory. (This may be
obvious to those who are students of literature, but that ain’t me!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merry New Year!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-title&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some may also note the nod to Tolkien in the title of this blog :) &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-title-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Weeks 11---12 &#x2F; Month 3</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w11-12/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w11-12/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w11-12/">&lt;p&gt;Another two weeks gone, and suddenly we’re at the end of the Calendar
Year.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-year-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-year&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not an idle two weeks but not the most productive either. A lot of personal
stuff—collecting the eldest from University, Christmas preparations and the
like.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some M.Phil. and Ph.D. application processing and candidate interviewing.
Knowledge transfer from Amjad before he leaves. Made some corrections to &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;emacs-eglot&#x2F;&quot;&gt;a past
blog post about Emacs &lt;code&gt;eglot&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. A bit of time spent trying
to get moving the two potential research projects that I didn’t anticipate:
starting to fill out a funding application for one, chasing the University over
some blocked industrial funding for the other.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-funding-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-funding&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial meetings about the M.Phil. research project I’m supervising this year.
Not strictly necessary due to the sabbatical, but the topic is bang on the
second of the two research projects mentioned above. Building on Amjad’s work,
the project will extend in two directions. First, determine whether his results
can be ported to the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.kernel.org&#x2F;doc&#x2F;html&#x2F;next&#x2F;scheduler&#x2F;sched-ext.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sched_ext&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a
scheduler class where behaviours can be written using BPF. Second, for added
&lt;del&gt;pain&lt;&#x2F;del&gt;excitement, do it on a Raspberry Pi as an example of a small(-ish) edge
device with a different architecture.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-year&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… vs Academic Year, which always begins on 1 October of course. As
does the Michaelmas Term. Which is of course not the Full Term. Because
Full Term is shorter than Term. Naturally. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-year-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-funding&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remain constantly amazed at how bad our processes around pursuing
and landing research funding are, from any funder really. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-funding-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 10</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w10/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w10/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w10/">&lt;p&gt;An odd week that. About 10 reference letters submitted throughout the week, the
latest about 30 minutes ago. Remember: a student is for life, not just a degree.
There was also a police statement to make following an unpleasant interaction on
a train. Apparently photos, CCTV and AI will all be involved seeking the
individual in question. Here’s hoping.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;figure class=&quot;fi fl pd1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;defence-in-progress.webp&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;The PhD defence in progress; yours truly on the right, furthest from the candidate&quot; width=&quot;360&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;PhD defence in progress.x&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the main event was the one it started with: the viva &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;sabbatical-diary-w6-9&#x2F;&quot;&gt;previously
mentioned&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tudelft.nl&#x2F;en&#x2F;&quot;&gt;TU
Delft&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. That was good fun: my first viva abroad
(indeed, my first outside England). People had told me it was different, being a
public defence, and it was: much &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;phd-viva&#x2F;&quot;&gt;more formal than ours&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with
much wearing of &lt;em&gt;paraphernalia&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (their word not mine :) doffing of caps (er,
doctors’ bonnets anyway), and so forth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;figure class=&quot;fi fr pd1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;success.webp&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;Post-defence selfie by the supervisor showing yours truly and the candidate.&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Post-defence selfie by the supervisor showing yours truly and the candidate.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was only when it finished that I finally realized why: the viva wasn’t just
the viva but also incorporated the graduation ceremony. Probably a good thing
that I didn’t take literally the part of the instructions where it said I could
wear whatever was customary at my own institution for a viva (shorts?
T-shirt?)—more appropriate would’ve been to wear what as customary for
graduation. Which I did.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was followed by two days of admissions interviewing. Technically I didn’t
need to do any this year due to the sabbatical but (&lt;em&gt;i&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) we were back up to
about 40—45 being interviewed so I thought I should help and (&lt;em&gt;ii&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;)
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;~djw1005&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Damon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; who has taken over as DOS while I’m
on sabbatical very kindly did several days interviewing for me last year while
he was on sabbatical. So there was at least a moral debt, now hopefully paid, at
least in part.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next: writing. No, really this time. Honest.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Weeks 6---9 &#x2F; Month 2</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w6-9/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w6-9/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w6-9/">&lt;p&gt;Hmm. So that was a blogging hiatus, not for any particularly good reason – just
a little busier than expected with a little less time in front of a computer
than needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;figure class=&quot;fi fr pd1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;roman-well.webp&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A top-down shot of a covered, backlit well in a Lancaster pub floor, apparently Roman&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A covered well in a Lancaster pub floor, apparently Roman.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spent the time reading dissertations and then carrying out Ph.D. vivas – one at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.lancaster.ac.uk&#x2F;scc&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Lancaster University&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, one at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.imperial.ac.uk&#x2F;design-engineering&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Imperial
College&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Currently en route to
the third, at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tudelft.nl&#x2F;tbm&#x2F;ess&#x2F;&quot;&gt;TU Delft&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Having done Ph.D.
vivas at a rate of slightly less than one every ~2 years since doing my own,
this has been a bit of a burst load. I think I might need to slow it back down
again!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wrote and submitted a rebuttal&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-rebuttal-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-rebuttal&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; for our ASPLOS 2026 submission on
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2508.15703&quot;&gt;Amjad’s excellent work&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I largely managed to
manage my temper while doing so—it’s rare I get a set of paper reviews without
at least one of them saying something I consider enraging, and this set was no
exception.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-reviews-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-reviews&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; Inevitably it made no difference—onwards and upwards to
OSDI. This is starting to feel like the &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;happy-day&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Unikernels ASPLOS’13
paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which I shall choose to treat as a good omen, for now
at least.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;figure class=&quot;fi fl pd1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;electric-pylon.webp&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A moody electric pylon looking towards some office buildings&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A moody electric pylon looking towards some office buildings.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Took part in the final plenary meeting for the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edgeless-project.eu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EU
EDGELESS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; project, which was fun.
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Gennevilliers&quot;&gt;Gennevilliers&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; may not be the most
picturesque part of Paris—though the electric pylons did have a slightly
Eiffel Tower-ish feel at times—but I enjoyed having dinner in &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;restaurants-de-france.fr&#x2F;fr&#x2F;au-rendez-vous-des-chauffeurs-gennevilliers-1981692.html&quot;&gt;the most French
truck-stop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
I’ve ever been into.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-truckstop-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-truckstop&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;figure class=&quot;fi fr pd1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lentil-stew.webp&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A delicious lentil stew with some smoked sausages floating&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A delicious lentil stew with some smoked sausages floating.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also managed to (finally!) nail a complete draft of that writing I mentioned.
Time to start circulating for feedback.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat unexpected work came along: some initially promising interest in
picking up some of the work we originally did for &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pages.cdbb.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;CDBB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
but targeted specifically at in-building heating and energy optimisation.
Several useful conversations already, looking forward to taking this further
through December and January. Will be interesting to see where we get to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less unexpected, though not anticipated, was that I won £14,000 from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tech.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;the
School&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to take Amjad’s work further with the
intent to complete on some industrial funding proposals currently in discussion.
Unfortunately&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-amjad-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-amjad&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; at the same time Amjad managed to land a role elsewhere so
we’re now in handover mode. C’est la vie.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next: finally make a start on the two research proposals originally planned, and
get the one on Amjad’s work that’s in development through to completion. And to
emit some of the posts currently trapped, half-written, in the pipeline.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll see.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-rebuttal&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pretty good rebuttal if I do say so myself. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-rebuttal-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-reviews&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m quite sure many of my reviews engender similar responses in
those authors unfortunate enough to have their papers reviewed by me. It seems
impossible to avoid—I’m not trying to get at anyone in particular here! &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-reviews-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-truckstop&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will confess that I haven’t been into many. But still. It was a very
nice lentil stew indeed, ! &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-truckstop-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-amjad&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…for me, not for him! &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-amjad-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 5</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w5/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w5/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w5/">&lt;p&gt;Another week gone, a little more done. Finally (albeit too slowly) progressing
some industrial funding through the system to go alongside the small grant
application of last week. Some other paperwork done.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polished this website a little as a reward—see the shiny new &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.brailleinstitute.org&#x2F;freefont&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Atkinson
Hyperlegible font&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for extra
readability. I started using it for all my windowing and editing setup so
thought I’d push it out here too. Maybe I’ll tweak the colour scheme one day too
:)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, external work completed, and jolly interesting it was too;
continued reading the Ph.D. dissertations that I’m examining—three to do
before Christmas; reviewed Eurosys’26 paper submissions. Nothing too exciting
really but progress of a sort on a couple of fronts, so not too bad.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next: writing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 4 &#x2F; Month 1</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w4/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w4/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w4/">&lt;p&gt;Well, that was a slightly slower week: it was school half-term so I had the
children for three days.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did manage to finally finish&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; polishing my Emacs
&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;treesitting-emacs&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tree-sitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;emacs-eglot&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Eglot&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; though.
Hopefully someone finds that useful, even if only future-me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also finally did a “proper” sabbatical thing and submitted a proposal for some
(small, local) funding to continue developing &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2508.15703&quot;&gt;Amjad’s excellent
work&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m travelling doing some external work this coming week in London, so I think
I’ll use some of the travel time to push the writing I said I’d do through to
completion so I can move on to more “proper” sabbatical work: developing
research funding proposals. And maybe if it all goes well I’ll even allow myself
some light coding as well – configuration polishing is all very well but it’s
not really the same!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now. Polishing configuration is never finished of course. A living
breathing thing and all that. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 3</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w3/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w3/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w3/">&lt;p&gt;Not much to say this week – largely more of the same. &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;treesitting-emacs&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Blogged about
&lt;code&gt;tree-sitter&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and (written, &lt;del&gt;to be published
shortly&lt;&#x2F;del&gt;now published!) &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;emacs-eglot&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;eglot&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, configuring both for an
increasing number of languages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also continued trying to land some small funding for continuing
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cst.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;people&#x2F;aati2&quot;&gt;Amjad’s&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; excellent work. Following
meticulous characterisation of Linux’s process scheduler, his Ph.D. developed an
alternative approach that enables a 30% smaller cluster to satisfy the same
“serverless” workload.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serverless computing is a popular style of cloud computing enabling customers to
ignore all application deployment details, instead encapsulating their
application – most commonly using “container” technology – so the platform can
take responsibility for providing the necessary resources for it to run, scaling
resources up and down in response to changes in demand. Providers typically
provision resources as a shared cluster of (physical or virtual) machines,
orchestrated using a cluster orchestrator based on the popular Kubernetes
orchestrator. That orchestrator is then responsible for running encapsulated
application code, ensuring each job is allocated sufficient resources.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cluster’s machines typically run Linux, and so it is Linux’s kernel
scheduler that is responsible for running a machine’s allocated jobs. That
scheduler’s behaviour is taken for granted by the plethora of work that has
sought to improve cluster performance. Unfortunately, close examination of
cluster performance results showed significant discrepancies when compared to
the intended behaviour – current practice masks these discrepancies by
over-provisioning the cluster.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meticulous examination of the results and the Linux kernel scheduler code
revealed that the behaviour of a particular core data structure in conjunction
with treatment of multi-core processors causes overheads to increase
disproportionately as demand increases. This increase in overheads is especially
prominent with serverless workloads due to their particular characteristics, and
causes the cluster orchestrator makes ever poorer job placement decisions. The
net effect is that, in practice, clusters must be significantly over-provisioned
to achieve acceptable performance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis reports how meticulous measurement revealed and unpicked this
problem, and describes and evaluates a set of relatively small – just a few
hundred lines of code – but critical changes in Linux’s kernel scheduler in
mitigation. The final outcome is that these mitigations allow an identical and
representative serverless workload to be supported by a cluster comprising 30%
fewer machines.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See our arXiv paper, “&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2508.15703&quot;&gt;Mitigating context switching in densely packed Linux
clusters with Latency-Aware Group Scheduling&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”
for more details :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Week 2</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w2/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w2/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w2/">&lt;p&gt;As predicted, this week was some Emacs configuration polishing interspersed with
some writing using &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;typst.app&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;typst&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I quite like &lt;code&gt;typst&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; I think
– it seems pretty capable, it’s pretty sensible, and it’s certainly easier to
read than LaTeX. And there’s even &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;imaginarytext.ca&#x2F;posts&#x2F;2024&#x2F;pandoc-typst-tutorial&#x2F;&quot;&gt;runes
available&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to invoke
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pandoc.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pandoc&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to allow production of body text in Markdown, to
be rendered using &lt;code&gt;typst&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as the backend. The piece of writing in question
didn’t go as fast as I wanted, but it did start in earnest. Which is, at least,
a start :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First cut at configuration polishing is also now done I think – now into
tweaking and refining as the different packages actually get used. Probably the
biggest improvement noticed so far is the use of
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;minad&#x2F;jinx&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;jinx&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; the “enchanted spell checker” which does
seem considerably better than the various &lt;code&gt;ispell&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&#x2F;&lt;code&gt;hunspell&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; incantation
packages I’ve historically used:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;common-lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;use-package&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; jinx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :diminish jinx-mode&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :hook (emacs-startup &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; global-jinx-mode)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :bind ((&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;C-;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; jinx-correct) (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;C-M-$&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; jinx-languages))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :config&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (vertico-multiform-mode)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (add-to-list&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;   &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;vertico-multiform-categories&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;   &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(jinx grid (vertico-grid-annotate &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #D33682;&quot;&gt; 20&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) (vertico-count &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #D33682;&quot;&gt; 4&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;:config&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; block integrates it with the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;minad&#x2F;vertico&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vertico&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; vertical completion system that
I’ve recently started using; simply remove if you don’t use that. This did also
require the NixOS package to be installed already:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;nix&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  programs&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;emacs&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;extraPackages&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #DC322F;&quot;&gt; =&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; epkgs:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; with&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; epkgs; ([ jinx ])&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #DC322F;&quot;&gt;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest visible change though was finally getting an auto-formatter for my
elisp code, specifically
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;rc-emacs&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;init.el&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; configured:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;common-lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;use-package&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; elisp-autofmt&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :commands (elisp-autofmt-mode elisp-autofmt-buffer)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :hook (emacs-lisp-mode &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; elisp-autofmt-mode))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensuring it is applied to &lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; simply required adding the (currently empty,
might become configuration in future apparently) flag file
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;rc-emacs&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;.elisp-autofmt&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;.elisp-autofmt&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to
my &lt;code&gt;~&#x2F;.emacs.d&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, and adding the following trailer to my
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;rc-emacs&#x2F;blob&#x2F;f06fc8fb9c280e11a8ddd8548ad245c8eba71484&#x2F;init.el#L1349-L1351&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;common-lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;;; Local variables:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;;; elisp-autofmt-load-packages-local: (&amp;quot;use-package&amp;quot; &amp;quot;use-package-core&amp;quot;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;;; end:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other big change has been moving to &lt;code&gt;tree-sitter&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;eglot&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; for language
support, but that’ll be a longer post so more on that later.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Sabbatical Diary: Weeks 0 &amp; 1</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w1/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w1/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sabbatical-diary-w1/">&lt;p&gt;Well, the sabbatical began. Your protagonist set off with a song in his heart
and the freedom to roam. And all that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what did I do? Well, initially I spent some time finishing up the handful of
things I hadn’t managed to do before 1 October came along. Tedious but probably
inevitable. If I forgot something you were waiting for, sorry – you may need to
remind me…!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then finally gave up on trying out new &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;vscodium.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ed&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;zed.dev&#x2F;&quot;&gt;it&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lap.dev&#x2F;lapce&#x2F;&quot;&gt;or&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;s – I
suspect the problem was largely me not them to be honest – and spent some
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;rc-emacs&quot;&gt;updating my emacs configuration&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; because
giving one’s tools a clean and polish occasionally seems a worthwhile thing plus
it eased me into a life of not attending committee meetings. Having done that
for a while, I rewarded myself by finishing off &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;bibtox&quot;&gt;a little bit of Python code I
have called &lt;code&gt;bibtox&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for processing my &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;publications&quot;&gt;BibTeX
files&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; so I can keep them well-formatted
as well as produce HTML output for &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;research&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. And I finally got
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;typst.app&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;typst&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; installed, began to learn how to use it at least a little bit,
and started writing. I also spent a few days travelling connected to some external work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So– perhaps not the most spectacularly interesting first week. But I made a
start. So there’s that. The plan for week 2 is to finish polishing my configuration and probably blog about at least some of the updates – emacs has moved on since I last looked – and then do some writing in earnest. Let’s see how I get on :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>All Change!</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/all-change/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/all-change/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/all-change/">&lt;p&gt;New (academic) year, new responsibilities. Or more precisely, far fewer
responsibilities :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m on sabbatical for this academic year&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; and, as a result, have been
required to give up almost all the various roles I’ve had over the past few
years. I keep being – or perhaps more precisely, revert to being – a
professor, of course, I’ll remain a Fellow of Christ’s College, and I’m allowed
to remain on the University Council.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-2-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; I’ll also retain external roles, like
my &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ipco.org.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;IPCO&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ipco.org.uk&#x2F;who-we-are&#x2F;technology-advisory-panel&#x2F;&quot;&gt;TAP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; membership.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;univ&#x2F;so&#x2F;&quot;&gt;University rules&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; mean that I
have to give up all teaching, admin and College Officer roles – everything
that’s not research basically. I’m allowed to supervise Ph.D. students and
remain on University Council, and that’s pretty much it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m not planning to supervise any Part II&#x2F;Part III&#x2F;M.Phil. projects, I won’t
be lecturing, Directing Studies, or supervising. Whatever will I do with
myself… Well, more on that later perhaps – I do have ideas if not yet actual
plans :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did notice one stupidity in the rules around sabbatical in the course of
applying for this one. I had always assumed sabbatical leave accrued at one
term in every seven (it does, cf. the sabbath), and that you could never
accrue more than one year (~ three terms) leave. But it turns out that’s not
quite correct – the actual rule is that &lt;em&gt;reckonable terms&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (those that
count toward sabbatical leave – so six reckonable terms gets you one term
of sabbatical leave) expire after six years. In my case I hit an edge case
as a result of having taken two terms sabbatical leave back in 2021 (Lent
and Easter terms 2021 to be precise). During periods of sabbatical leave,
the clock keeps ticking to expire reckonable terms already accrued. The
result was that when I came to apply for this year’s sabbatical leave, I was
actually two reckonable terms short – they’d fallen off the end due to the
expiry clock not stopping while I was on leave in 2021. Fortunately, while
HR wanted me to ask my Faculty to “mortgage” two future reckonable terms,
there was another route: the Faculty Board can just declare that they’re
going to count the expired terms anyway. And, happily, they did. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also remain a member of most of the various committees of Council that
I’m on, though I’m exempted from attending meetings. By which it turns out
is meant &lt;em&gt;forbidden&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; from attending meetings. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-2-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Systematising the obvious</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/research-matrix/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/research-matrix/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/research-matrix/">&lt;p&gt;Ok, so this is one of those that comes about because I found myself saying the
same thing to different people a couple of times within a week or so. Which I
usually think means I should probably write it down.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been talking with Ph.D. students about selecting research topics, doing
research, and what is interesting subsequently to report in papers. In doing so
I recalled some advice that was given to me during my Ph.D. — so I’m not taking
credit for this, though I can’t recall who specifically said it to me like this
first; possibly Ralph Becket. What follows is of course scoped to computer
systems research as far as I’m concerned, though it may well apply more broadly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;figure class=&quot;fi fr pd1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;research-matrix.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A plain whiteboard sketch of the matrix described in the main text&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A whiteboard sketch of the obvious&#x2F;successful matrix.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, to the point. I have sometimes found it useful to think about research
topics and their results as placed along two axes, each of which I split into
two categories. The first axis might be labelled &lt;em&gt;obviousness&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with the two
categories labelled “&lt;em&gt;obviously…&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;” and “&lt;em&gt;non-obviously…&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;”.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; The second
axis might be labelled &lt;em&gt;success&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with the two categories “&lt;em&gt;…works&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;” and
“&lt;em&gt;…doesn’t work&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;”. Finally, I put an indicator in each quadrant as to the
desirability of work in that quadrant – shown in the picture as ticks (the more
ticks, the more desirable), or crosses (undesirable).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering each of the quadrants then, we have in order of desirability:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;non-obviously works&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Bingo! This is when you’ve done something that
people didn’t think would work but it turns out you had sufficient insight,
skill, luck, resources, or whatever to make it work. Reporting this sort of
work is happy times – fame, glory, riches, the prize. No, wait, that’s not
right. Oh yes — you get a good published paper. Nice.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;obviously works&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: The bulk of published research in my experience.
Certainly not bad, and definitely contributing to knowledge. But not really
surprising — unlikely to create that elusive “wow! that’s cool!” feeling.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;non-obviously doesn’t work&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Far too little of this sort of thing is
published in my opinion. I feel quite pleased when I manage work like this
because I don’t need to care quite so much as I used to about getting papers
accepted and I find the process and outcome interesting. But it is sometimes
hard to get this work out there as it often seems too easy for reviewers to
focus on the fact the thing didn’t work rather than considering the
contribution you’ve made by showing that everyone else’s intuitions are
wrong. Sad but mildly self-righteous times ensue.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;obviously doesn’t work&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: No-one cares. Tends to get a big “yeah? and?
idiot” from reviewers. I wouldn’t usually bother except as a personal
learning exercise.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I realise that the more natural word here would have been
&lt;em&gt;surprisingly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Sigh. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Orating honours</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/orating-honors/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/orating-honors/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/orating-honors/">&lt;p&gt;This is a bit of a niche one but – here in &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cambridge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
we have a number of quaint &#x2F; historic &#x2F; weird &#x2F; cool (take your pick)
traditions. One that I think is at the quite cool end is that, when we award
honorary degrees, the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;glossary.lib.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;term&#x2F;orator&quot;&gt;University
Orator&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; writes and delivers an
oration introducing the honorand and explaining why they’re getting the degree.
In Latin. And, occasionally, also with fragments in Greek and Sindarin.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-elvish-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-elvish&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
And when I say “delivers”, I really mean “performs” based on what I saw when in
the audience for the honorary degree ceremony this year for the first time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happily, as we’re not totally behind the times, English translations are also
provided, in &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reporter.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;the Reporter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; naturally.
And I decided to take a look back through some as I thought some of the ones I
saw this year were pretty good. And as it was a slow Sunday afternoon, I went
back as far as the online Reporter allowed. And here are the results – a list
of links to all of the oration texts that are online, with some honorands called
out where I thought they were particularly cool or interesting or
moving,&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-moving-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-moving&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; or I’d heard of the recipient.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-culture-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-culture&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Honorands&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2024-25&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6791&#x2F;section7.shtml#heading2-12&quot;&gt;2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Stormzy&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2023-24&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6747&#x2F;section4.shtml#heading2-9&quot;&gt;2024&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Kip Thorne&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2022-23&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6706&#x2F;6706.pdf#page=22&quot;&gt;2023&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2021-22&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6664&#x2F;6664.pdf#page=17&quot;&gt;2022&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-absentia-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-absentia&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Roger Penrose • Simon Schama&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2020&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;no ceremony due to the COVID-19 pandemic so none conferred&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2018-19&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6553&#x2F;section5.shtml#heading2-14&quot;&gt;2019&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Doreen Lawrence • Jane Goodall&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2017-18&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6512&#x2F;section7.shtml#heading2-16&quot;&gt;2018&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Borys • Michael Edwards&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2016-17&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6471&#x2F;section8.shtml#heading2-22&quot;&gt;2017&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Stephanie Shirley • Sophie Wilson • Manuel Castells&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2015-16&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6431&#x2F;section9.shtml#heading2-48&quot;&gt;2016&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; [&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2015-16&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6431&#x2F;6431-CambridgeHonoraryDegrees-2016.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;]&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Keith Peters • Jonny Ive&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2014-15&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6392&#x2F;section7.shtml#heading2-23&quot;&gt;2015&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; [&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2014-15&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6392&#x2F;6392-CambridgeHonoraryDegrees-2015.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;]&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Julia Neuberger • Neil Macgregor&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2013-14&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6353&#x2F;section6.shtml#heading2-18&quot;&gt;2014&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; [&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2013-14&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6353&#x2F;6353-Honorary-Degrees-June2014.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;]&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Albie Sachs • Yusuf Hamied • Martin Rees • Ian Mckellan&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2012-13&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6315&#x2F;Cambridge_Honorary_Degree_Congregation_2013.pdf&quot;&gt;2013&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Hilary Mantel&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2011-12&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6273&#x2F;hon_degrees_2012.pdf&quot;&gt;2012&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Peter Higgs • Alfred Brendel&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2010-11&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6231&#x2F;hon_degs_2011.pdf&quot;&gt;2011&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2009-10&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6195&#x2F;section12.shtml#heading2-49&quot;&gt;2010&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; [&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2009-10&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6195&#x2F;honorary_degrees.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;]&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Andrew Wiles • Evelyn Glennie&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2008-09&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6156&#x2F;25.html&quot;&gt;2009&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; [&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2008-09&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6156&#x2F;acta.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;]&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;The Aga Khan • Melinda Gates • Bill Gates • Shirley Williams • William Broecker [ global warming ] • Amartya Sen&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2007-08&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6117&#x2F;29.html&quot;&gt;2008&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;John Sentamu&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2006-07&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6080&#x2F;20.html&quot;&gt;2007&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Hans Blix • Ann Cotton • Onora O’Neill • Nicholas Stern&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2005-06&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6043&#x2F;26.html&quot;&gt;2006&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2004-05&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6006&#x2F;23.html&quot;&gt;2005&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2003-04&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;5968&#x2F;34.html&quot;&gt;2004&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Robert Horvitz • Quentin Blake • John Dankworth • Cleo Laine&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2002-03&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;5930&#x2F;28.html&quot;&gt;2003&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Alan Macdiarmid • John Sulston • John Adams&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2001-02&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;5891&#x2F;15.html&quot;&gt;2002&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2000-01&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;5851&#x2F;45.html&quot;&gt;2001&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sydney Brenner • Mamphela Ramphele • Margaret Atwood&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;1999-2000&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;5817&#x2F;17.html&quot;&gt;2000&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;1998-99&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;5781&#x2F;25.html&quot;&gt;1999&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Desmond Tutu • Gordon Moore • Miriam Rothschild&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;1997-98&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;5744&#x2F;4.html&quot;&gt;1998&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Aung San Suu Kyi (in absentia!) • Barbara Castle • Helmut Kohl • Aaron Klug&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…and there, sadly, the Reporter online record ends.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-elvish&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elvish to those not well versed in Tolkien. I once posted to
&lt;code&gt;rec.arts.sf.tolkien&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Just saying. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-elvish-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-moving&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously. See, for example, those for &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2018-19&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6553&#x2F;section5.shtml#heading2-14&quot;&gt;Doreen
Lawrence&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
or &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.admin.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;reporter&#x2F;2013-14&#x2F;weekly&#x2F;6353&#x2F;6353-Honorary-Degrees-June2014.pdf&quot;&gt;Yusuf
Hamied&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-moving-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-culture&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not particularly well-versed in culture, being mostly a geek of
sorts. Whatevs. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-culture-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-absentia&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Included celebration of those conferred in absentia in 2021 due to
COVID-19. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-absentia-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Whither AI?</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/whither-ai/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/whither-ai/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/whither-ai/">&lt;p&gt;I am hardly the first person to comment&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; on this – I am given to understand
AI has been a topic of some interest to many for a few years now. I’m sure I’ve
seen, and possibly even &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mastodon.me.uk&#x2F;@mort&quot;&gt;re-tooted&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; things about
it in fact. I’m afraid I just don’t keep up.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But recent experiences reviewing for a couple of systems&#x2F;networking venues has
led me to feel I need to ask: &lt;strong&gt;WHY&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;? More pointedly, why does the following
seem like good motivation for a research paper?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a complex and important task that currently requires considerable
expertise to carry out because it is important to be precise and get it
right.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The task in question can be described imprecisely using natural language by
non-experts.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI (inevitably, some large-language model) can take that natural language
description and, after training, produce some output that is stochastically
like unto what an expert might produce given the same underlying problem,
having brought to bear their expertise.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus we build an AI that can take the non-expert’s imprecise description and
show that sometimes the output it produces is not so wrong as to fail some
&lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; tests of utility that we introduce.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on things I’ve recently reviewed “not so wrong” above means “error rate of
no more than 25—30% when taking expertly generated natural language prompts as
input”. Which is to say, probably not the sorts of input prompt that a
non-expert might produce.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network configuration and management is the domain I’ve seen this argument made
in most recently. Which seems quite strange to me because I always thought that
a 25% error rate in configuring, e.g., your enterprise network security
perimeter would be bad. But apparently not if it’s done by an AI.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More generally, why do we want to build tools that allow untrained experts to do
a job when mistakes are high impact, it requires a trained expert to detect
those mistakes, and those tools &lt;em&gt;by design&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; only produce statistically valid
output? An error rate of once in a blue moon is categorically worse than a zero
error rate if the error involved can leave your entire digital estate open to
compromise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the big issue here is that experts sometimes make typos when editing the
configuration files, maybe building some domain-specific languages or better
user interfaces or verification techniques or other tooling would be a better
way to help them not do that than replacing them with tools that &lt;strong&gt;by design&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;
are only ever probably about right.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So please stop justifying your AI application research by saying simply that it
allows non-experts to carry out expert work! I’m much more likely to be
convinced by uses of AI that make experts &lt;em&gt;more productive&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; – though don’t get
me started on how to measure productivity because I don’t know except via means
which are expensive and time consuming, and it really seems that very few people
can be bothered doing that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok fine. I admit it. This is a rant. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Artificial Intelligence, but at what cost?</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/sermonising/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/sermonising/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/sermonising/">&lt;p&gt;Our inestimable and most excellent Chaplain, Revd Dr Helen Orchard, likes to
have a theme for the Sunday evensong services for the term. Back in Michaelmas
2023 it was … AI. I said I’d help find someone to give a sermon from a
technical perspective but then signally failed to do so (sorry!). So in the end
I said I’d do it, even though AI is not my thing and I’d never given a sermon
before. Or, for that matter, attended evensong. Take the opportunities offered
and all that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realised this week that, although a few people at the time had asked for
copies, I’d also done nothing about that (I am nothing if not consistently
rubbish). So here’s the text, more or less as given, on 15 October 2023. Note
that the golden eagle I mount is a rather fine lectern in our Chapel (pictured).
Nothing more salacious than that. Filthy minds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three editorial notes given that it’s been over a year and a half since I gave
this (my! how time flies…):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I allude to this but should be clear: the neural network is not the only
technological approach to producing AI – several others exist and are both
useful and used, machine learning being one that’s particularly productive in
recent years. However the most hyped was and still seems to be various forms
of neural network so that’s what I focused on.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I refer to “static datasets” because the versions of ChatGPT at the time were
trained infrequently on a given dataset of the moment. Training updates now
seem much more frequent (perhaps weekly), user context is maintained
throughout a chat session, and user feedback sought at the end. So while it’s
still technically true that the datasets involved are static, it’s much less
noticeable.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The example of “God save the” worked particularly because this was only about
a year after Queen Elizabeth II died, so “queen” was likely still the
instinctive response of many.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, just in case it’s not clear – I tend toward the sceptical end
regarding AI. Potentially a useful tool in some circumstances but all claims
about AGI are nonsense and the singularity won’t happen because of the machines.
Human stupidity on the other hand seems without bound. And always follow the
money.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;figure class=&quot;fi fr pd1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.christs.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;facilities&#x2F;chapel&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;Christ&#x27;s College Chapel 6.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of a fine golden-coloured lectern, the head of which is an eagle&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#x27;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.christs.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;sites&#x2F;default&#x2F;files&#x2F;inline-images&#x2F;Christ%27s%20College%20Chapel%206.jpg&#x27;&gt;A photograph of a fine golden-coloured lectern, the head of which is an eagle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mount the golden eagle for the first time, I should say that I am not
normally given to preaching – though my children might disagree with that
statement – but as the theme this term is Artificial Intelligence, Helen
asked me to speak to you about that from the perspective of a computer
scientist. Unless you catch me in a pub after a couple of pints, I am also not
given to philosophising, so I will limit myself to the physical reality of
&lt;em&gt;Artificial Intelligence&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;AI&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Specifically, what is it and what does it
cost. I will use AIs that generate text as examples, as these so-called &lt;em&gt;Large
Language Models&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; have been the focus of considerable interest in recent
months, but the same basic mechanisms and problems apply to AIs used to
generate images, music, videos and so on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, what is it. AI is a catch-all term for a set of technologies that
attempt to replicate whatever we call “intelligence”. Computer scientists,
cognitive psychologists and mathematicians have worked on these various
technologies for decades, but the current vogue is very much for a particular
set of mathematical techniques that try to produce brain-like behaviour by
modelling inter-connected neurons.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each neuron is stimulated by one or more input signals which it combines to
produce an output signal with some probability. The outputs of some neurons
are connected to the inputs of some other neurons, creating an enormous
network. The effect in our brains might be that an input signal “I want a
biscuit” results in an output signal that causes us to move an arm to pick up
a biscuit. In a modern “generative AI”, the input might be a sentence or
paragraph or two of text, and the resulting output might be an image or a
sequence of words.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a simple example of what I mean, if I asked you to give the next few words
in the phrase starting “God save the” you might say “king send him
victorious”. You have just performed inference using your own language model,
generating some likely output text given three words of input. I’ll come back
to that example later.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said the inputs were combined to produce the output with some probability,
but how exactly? The process for combining inputs involves a set of parameters
that are determined by finding the values that give the best fit some a priori
data. This is known as training if you’re an AI specialist, or parameter
fitting if you’re a statistician.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple analogy: you may recall that a straight line is defined by two
parameters, its slope and any point on the line. If you had a set of two
dimensional data points that you thought were straightforwardly related, you
might try to discover that relationship by drawing the best straight line you
could through them; but which particular line would you think was the best? A
reasonable choice might be the one that minimised the total distance from the
line to each point. For an AI the maths is a little more complex, but that’s
basically what happens: training finds the parameter values that give the best
fit to a large set of training data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s a modern AI: a statistical model that, when stimulated by one or
more inputs, produces outputs with some probability. The inputs might be words
or images or some other thing, and the outputs might be words or images or
some other thing. The underlying model might be wrapped up by other models
that, for example, try to filter out undesirable outputs or provide for
different ways of consuming inputs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the sheer scale that makes this work: your brain has perhaps 100 billion
neurons each of which might connect to 10,000 other neurons for a total of
perhaps one million billion connections, whereas an AI such as a recent
version of ChatGPT might have 175 billion parameters but each connected to
just hundreds of others. The underlying mathematics has been known for
decades; it is the combination of massive training datasets and the enormous
computational resources of the cloud that have enabled us to build these AIs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, ignoring the hysteria around so-called Artificial General Intelligence
and The Singularity, what costs do these AIs incur?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To return to the example I used, I said that you might have completed the
phrase “God save the” with the words “king send him victorious”. In some sense
that is the “correct” completion. But perhaps some of you would have initially
thought “queen send her victorious”. And I have at least one friend who would
naturally respond “queen and her fascist regime”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human experience is varied and personal – the training process I described
typically uses large static datasets collected by scraping the Internet. While
the resulting AI can be configured not always to produce identical outputs
given identical inputs, the training process does naturally lead to a kind of
homogenisation. Simplistically, if your group is not represented in that
training dataset, its experience will not be represented in the AI and thus
will not be reproduced in the output. Worse, if the training data contains
misrepresentations or attacks on your group, the AI will by default capture
and perpetuate them, already observed to be a particular problem for women,
Jews, and many minorities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, I mentioned that training data is scraped from the Internet – but as
the musical Avenue Q famously put it, “the Internet is for porn”. A lot of
that text is rather fantastical and describes actions generally unacceptable
in polite society, so the companies producing and operating AIs try to create
guardrails by building other models that filter offensive outputs generated by
their AIs – but how do you train such a model? You need to start with
examples of offensive output that are labelled as such so that you can train a
model to differentiate between what is offensive and what is inoffensive. But
creating that labelled data involves human labour. For example, OpenAI were
reported as outsourcing this activity to workers in Kenya paid less than $2
per day to label perhaps 200 paragraphs per day of offensive input text with
the type of offensiveness: rape, torture, incest, and so on. Unpleasant and
psychologically damaging work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also more practical problems posed by the resources used to create
and operate AIs. In particular, energy and water.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes a lot of computation to train and operate a large popular AI –
OpenAI reported about three and a half thousand petaflops-per-second-days in
2020 to train their GPT model, where a petaflop represents a million billion
computations. That is, about 10 years of a computer running at one petaflop
per second. For comparison, your phone might achieve 0.1% of that performance.
But as the bumper sticker has it, the cloud is just someone else’s computer –
in the case of a training run for a large AI model, several hundred thousand
computers in a datacenter. For example, Microsoft’s Iowa datacenter was built
out for training models for OpenAI and has 285,000 standard processor cores
and 10,000 GPUs (more powerful and power-hungry processors that you might be
familiar with using if you’re a gamer).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sub&gt; from the energy to power the computers plus water to
cool them. How much? Well, estimates computed for earlier, smaller, models put
the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sub&gt; footprint of a single training run at roughly the same as a
round-trip flight from New York to San Francisco. Once trained, individual
queries are comparatively cheap – but ChatGPT experienced the fastest ever
growth of an Internet service. Earlier this year it was estimated as serving
hundreds of millions of queries per day resulting in power consumption of
perhaps 1 gigawatt-hour each day – the equivalent of 33,000 American
households.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for water, Microsoft has reported that its global water usage increased 34%
from 2021 to 2022; Google’s increased 20% in the same period, but from a
higher baseline. The increase is believed to be substantially due to training
and operating AI. A group from University of California at Riverside estimate
that each “conversation” with ChatGPT uses, directly and indirectly, about a
pint of water – and this generally needs to be clean drinking water that will
not leave residues that clog systems. The month before GPT-4 training was
completed, Microsoft’s Iowa datacenters consumed 11.5 million gallons, about
6% of the district’s drinking water. The amounts vary based on season and
location of the datacenter but it seems clear that water consumption is very
substantial and could impact local communities and ecosystems. And of course,
there is a tension here: cheap and green solar energy improves the carbon
footprint but the associated higher temperatures usually also worsens the
water footprint as more cooling is required.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there’s a view of AI – an impressive set of mathematical and computational
techniques that can recreate some human behaviours to some extent in some
circumstances, at significant practical and moral cost. My own view is
threefold.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, using the phrase “Artificial Intelligence” to describe these
technologies, rather than something less emotive such as Computationally
Intensive Statistics, inevitably generates a very strong hype cycle, and we
are currently at a point in that cycle where a welcome degree of scepticism is
starting to come in and people are more actively questioning what exactly
these technologies can and can’t do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we have largely proceeded to date without concern for any of the costs
I discussed earlier, and – also welcome – that is changing: the costs are
significant and we cannot ignore them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, there are interesting legal and economic tussles taking place as to who
owns the training data, who owns the weights – that is, the AIs – produced,
and by whom and how should AIs be regulated. In particular, it is notable that
many companies are claiming that there is a need for regulatory barriers to be
introduced – but those are the companies that have already reached a scale
where they can overcome those barriers, so such barriers will serve only to
keep newcomers out of the marketplace, entrenching the existing power of “big
tech” (OpenAI, Google, Microsoft, Amazon, Meta, etc).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as I used the word hysteria earlier to describe hyped fears of
Artificial General Intelligence and the Singularity – &lt;strong&gt;please&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; be sceptical
of anyone claiming that as a serious existential risk, &lt;strong&gt;particularly&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; if
they are associated with aforementioned “big tech”! I view most of that
discourse as a “dead cat” strategy, an attempt to distract from the current
harms they are causing today by pointing to vague, nebulous, yet potentially
infinite future harms. For more about the quite startling beliefs of many of
those sounding those alarms, I recommend reading about the TESCREAL set of
ideologies – Transhumanism, Extropianism, Singularitarianism, Cosmism,
Rationalism, Effective Altruism, Longtermism.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank-you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#references&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: references&quot;&gt;References&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#background&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Language Models are Few-Shot Learners”, OpenAI, 2020.
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2005.14165&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2005.14165&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“On the Dangers of Stochastic Parrots: Can Language Models Be Too Big?”,
Bender et al, FAcct’21. &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3442188.3445922&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3442188.3445922&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“The Internet is for porn”, Stephanie D’Abruzzo &amp;amp; Rick Lyon, Avenue Q.
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;genius.com&#x2F;Stephanie-dabruzzo-and-rick-lyon-the-internet-is-for-porn-lyrics&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;genius.com&#x2F;Stephanie-dabruzzo-and-rick-lyon-the-internet-is-for-porn-lyrics&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;hidden-work&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#hidden-work&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: hidden-work&quot;&gt;Hidden Work&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“OpenAI Used Kenyan Workers on Less Than $2 Per Hour to Make ChatGPT Less
Toxic”, Time.com, 2023,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;time.com&#x2F;6247678&#x2F;openai-chatgpt-kenya-workers&#x2F;&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;time.com&#x2F;6247678&#x2F;openai-chatgpt-kenya-workers&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Behind the secretive work of the many, many humans helping to train AI”,
NPR, 2023.
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.npr.org&#x2F;2023&#x2F;06&#x2F;26&#x2F;1184392406&#x2F;behind-the-secretive-work-of-the-many-many-humans-helping-to-train-ai&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.npr.org&#x2F;2023&#x2F;06&#x2F;26&#x2F;1184392406&#x2F;behind-the-secretive-work-of-the-many-many-humans-helping-to-train-ai&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#energy&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: energy&quot;&gt;Energy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Energy and Policy Considerations for Deep Learning in NLP”, Strubell et al,
2019. &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1906.02243&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1906.02243&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Training a single AI model can emit as much carbon as five cars in their
lifetimes”, MIT Technology Review, 2019.
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;2019&#x2F;06&#x2F;06&#x2F;239031&#x2F;training-a-single-ai-model-can-emit-as-much-carbon-as-five-cars-in-their-lifetimes&#x2F;&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;2019&#x2F;06&#x2F;06&#x2F;239031&#x2F;training-a-single-ai-model-can-emit-as-much-carbon-as-five-cars-in-their-lifetimes&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;water&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#water&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: water&quot;&gt;Water&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Artificial intelligence technology behind ChatGPT was built in Iowa — with a
lot of water”, AP News, 2023.
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apnews.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;chatgpt-gpt4-iowa-ai-water-consumption-microsoft-f551fde98083d17a7e8d904f8be822c4&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apnews.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;chatgpt-gpt4-iowa-ai-water-consumption-microsoft-f551fde98083d17a7e8d904f8be822c4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“A.I. tools fueled a 34% spike in Microsoft’s water consumption, and one city
with its data centers is concerned about the effect on residential supply”,
Fortune, 2023.
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fortune.com&#x2F;2023&#x2F;09&#x2F;09&#x2F;ai-chatgpt-usage-fuels-spike-in-microsoft-water-consumption&#x2F;&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fortune.com&#x2F;2023&#x2F;09&#x2F;09&#x2F;ai-chatgpt-usage-fuels-spike-in-microsoft-water-consumption&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Making AI Less “Thirsty”: Uncovering and Addressing the Secret Water
Footprint of AI Models“, Pengfei Li et al, 2023.
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2304.03271&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2304.03271&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Coping and Capping</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/coping-and-capping/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/coping-and-capping/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/coping-and-capping/">&lt;p&gt;Well that was fun! Quite high up there in the set of things that I never even
considered I might do would’ve been awarding degrees. But by dint of being
President and thus standing in for
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Simon_McDonald%2C_Baron_McDonald_of_Salford&quot;&gt;Simon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
on Saturday I did exactly that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&quot;coped.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;Me, coped and capped in the superman cape and mortarboard&quot; width=&quot;360&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University held a Congregation for those being admitted to the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cambridgestudents.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;your-course&#x2F;graduation-and-what-next&#x2F;cambridge-ma&quot;&gt;Cambridge
MA&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
(“Magistri in Artibus” – Master of Arts). Degrees are conferred by the
Chancellor, Vice-Chancellor or nominated deputy. Apparently, typically, for this
one and the main undergraduate congregation in July, that nominated deputy
Vice-Chancellor is usually the Head of House for the College concerned. In this
case, as President at Christ’s is effectively deputy Master (~ Head of House),
it me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead of the usual Batman-style black gown, I got to wear the rather natty
Superman-style &lt;em&gt;cope&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, hence I was &lt;em&gt;coped&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I also got to wear one of the fancy
hats (“square cap” or mortarboard) for the first time, hence I was also
&lt;em&gt;capped&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as many other officers were also appropriately hatted, and out of respect
to the role would &lt;em&gt;cap&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; me at many available opportunities, the written advice I
received was literally that “officers will cap you – you do not have to cap
back” because the cope makes it difficult to do so.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in brief, it seems I coped with being coped and capped but could not cope
with capping while coped. To add to the excitement, I also had to Do Some Latin.
Thankfully it’s a dead language so I assume all it could do was turn in its
grave while I butchered it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope everyone had a good time anyway!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Rewarding influence</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;2025.eurosys.org&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;EuroSys 2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; was co-located with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; this year. Other
commitments meant I (again) couldn’t stay for the whole conference, attending
primarily because &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;tdis-accepted&#x2F;&quot;&gt;two students had papers in the TDIS
workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&quot;stage.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of me in a yellow t-shirt receiving the award&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But happily I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; able to stay for the first day of the conference –
“happily” not only because it gave me a chance to catch up with some old friends
I hadn’t seen in a decade or more, but also because &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;2451116.2451167&quot;&gt;the Mirage unikernels
paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which appeared at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;asplos13.rice.edu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2013&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; won one of two &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&#x2F;awards&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS 2025 Influential Papers
awards&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is obviously very flattering – typically doing research is necessarily its
own reward because the work can seem fruitless much of the time. Even when a
paper gets written and submitted it will most likely be rejected – I think
EuroSys this year reported something like a 12% acceptance rate, so rejection is
&lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the most likely outcome. Finally, if the paper does finally get
accepted, it will most likely sink without trace – perhaps a brief flurry of
interest for a few months or so, the paper gets cited a few times, and then it
fades away. This seems inevitable in a reasonably fast moving field that is also
growing at pace – EuroSys had ~160 attendees in 2006, growing to ~330 in the 10
years to 2016, but hitting ~1100 this year; while submissions grew from ~200 in
2019 to 696 this year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&quot;official.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of the certificate&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to win an award recognising that others feel a paper actually had some
influence is rare, and makes me very happy :) At the same time, it reinforces a
couple of lessons that I really should’ve internalised by now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is that papers inevitably get better for thoughtful considered
feedback from experts a step or several away from the work – so drafts should
be produced in plenty of time and distributed to anyone who’s willing to take
the time for feedback. In the case of this paper the previous failed submission
to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usenix.org&#x2F;conference&#x2F;osdi12&quot;&gt;OSDI 2012&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; had, let’s say, reviews
of mixed quality. But one stood out, from Jon Howell (who signs his reviews so I
know it was him), who gave us a firm “reject” which (in retrospect) was actually
fairly well-deserved but in an incredibly constructive way. To paraphrase him
slightly, the work was interesting but the paper was crap – &lt;em&gt;and here’s how to
rewrite it so it makes sense&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. We basically did what he said, ASPLOS accepted
it, and the rest is now history. (Over a decade ago, good grief.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is that I simply cannot predict whether any research I’m doing is
actually going to turn out to have any value. The only other equivalent award
I’ve had was an &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;infocom2024.ieee-infocom.org&#x2F;awards&quot;&gt;INFOCOM 2024 Test of Time
award&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1109&#x2F;INFCOM.2012.6195845&quot;&gt;our 2012 paper on a
system called &lt;em&gt;Thinkair&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, about
mobile-code offload from devices to the cloud. That paper had received
considerably more than just one rejection prior to acceptance, and if I recall
my final contribution correctly, I recommended not submitting it to INFOCOM as I
didn’t think we’d done enough to address previous review comments.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shows what I know. But then, how boring would life be without a little
ignorance… :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Not one but two accepted papers and a Ph.D.</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/">&lt;p&gt;As I find myself once more on a train to parts unknown (to me at least), a brief
update :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parts unknown in question is Rotterdam, NL (so really quite well-known to
quite a lot of people, just not me) for &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;2025.eurosys.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EURO&#x2F;SYS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (being held jointly with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, although I can’t stay for
the whole thing unfortunately) and specifically the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tdis.gitlab.io&#x2F;tdis25&#x2F;&quot;&gt;3rd International Workshop
of Testing Distributed Internet of Things Systems
(TDIS)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Happily the programme committee decided to accept two papers from my
(ex-)students – which is nice :) The two in question are&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3719159.3721222&quot;&gt;Reckon-ing Kubernetes at the Edge using Emulated
Clusters&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; with Alessandro Sassi
(University of Cambridge &#x2F; Politecnico di Milano) and Christopher Jensen
(University of Cambridge &#x2F; Microsoft Research). This describes Alessandro’s
M.Sc. research project undertaken as a visitor with my group. He built on
Chris’ earlier work on &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3447851.3458739&quot;&gt;Reckon, an emulator setup for examining consensus
system behaviour&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Alessandor
extended this to use ContainerNet enabling it to emulate Kubernetes clusters
on a single node, and used this to examine Kubernetes performance in some
edge network scenarios. Source available on GitHub at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;AleSassi&#x2F;reckon-k8s&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;AleSassi&#x2F;reckon-k8s&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3719159.3721221&quot;&gt;LoRaLive: Efficient LoRaWAN Traffic
Generation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; with Vadim Safronov
(University of Oxford &#x2F; University of Cambridge). This reports a component of
Vadim’s Ph.D. work where he built a system to enable dense deployment LoRaWAN
trace-playback using a minimal number of nodes while respecting legal
constraints on duty cycles. Source available on GitHub at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;LoRaLive&#x2F;LoRaLive&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;LoRaLive&#x2F;LoRaLive&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both nice tools that we hope might be of community interest!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ph.D. in question is Chris Jensen’s – happily he passed his viva on
Thursday just gone, titled “Separating conflict-recovery from failure-recovery
in distributed consensus”, examined by &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;timharris.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tim Harris&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;charap.co&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Aleksey Charapko&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Other recent passes include Al-Amjad
Tawfiq Isstaif, titled “Contention-resilient overcommitment for serverless
deployments” and Andrew Jeffery, titled “Modelling orchestration”. The race&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
is now on for the first to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;techreports&#x2F;&quot;&gt;tech
report&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not really a race. That would be weird. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>PhD viva, UK style</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/">&lt;p&gt;Having recently, happily, had several PhD students completing in short order,
I’ve been approaching external PhD examiners. Occasionally I find myself asking
someone who’s not done any &#x2F; many in the UK previously. As our system – as all
such systems! – is a bit different to those in other parts of the world, I’ve
written a few notes on a couple of occasions about what to expect. So I figured
I might as well publish them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is my impression &#x2F; understanding based on experience here in the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cst.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Department of Computer Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cambridge University&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; ca. 2025. Your Mileage May Vary
anywhen and anywhere else, including anywhere else in the UK – check local
regulations to be sure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of process, the system here is that candidates submit their complete
dissertation and then undergo a “viva voce” (oral examination). It would be
usual for the viva to take place within 2—3 months of submission. It’s better
(IMO, much better) if it can happen in person but we may still be able to
arrange to do it online in extremis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two examiners:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;internal examiner&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (typically connected to the Department) who ensures
the process is followed properly but may not be a deep expert in the specific
topic, and&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;external examiner&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (from outside the University) who is there as the
subject matter expert.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The viva consists of the two examiners asking the candidate questions about
their dissertation until they’re satisfied; typically this takes at least 2h and
can go longer, though more than 3.5—4h is unusual in my experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examiners are each expected to read the dissertation in detail before the
viva and each write a short (typically 1—2pp) independent report giving their
opinion, outlining any concerns they will have and the resulting
topics&#x2F;questions they will be exploring in the viva, and indicating what their a
priori judgement is in terms of recommendation (roughly: pass&#x2F;pass with
corrections&#x2F;revise &amp;amp; resubmit&#x2F;no Ph.D. but you can have a Masters&#x2F;fail).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examiners will then typically meet ~30min or so before the viva to discuss
their independent reports and decide on the approach to take in the viva. After
the viva they write a joint report (usually shorter than their independent
reports; perhaps 0.5pp) outlining what happened in the viva, as well as making a
final recommendation and providing (if appropriate) a list of corrections that
must be satisfied for the candidate to pass.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the University pays a (risibly small) honorarium to the external
examiner for doing the viva plus reasonable expenses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Workshopping, across the universe</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/">&lt;p&gt;One of the pleasures of being an academic is to travel to nice places to meet
interesting people, and interesting places to meet nice people. In one of my
first such trips for a few years I recently went to Sweden to participate in the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;17th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;17th Cloud Control Workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;17th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;photo.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of the presenter in front of a slide&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d previously attended the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;15th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;15th Cloud Control
Workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; shortly before the pandemic
happened, causing the series to pause briefly. This was the reboot, and as
before, it was a great deal of fun: good company, good food, beautiful location.
If you get the chance to go, take it if you can!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop is a really nice mix of keynote presentations – not too many and
not too long at 20 minutes (mostly) – and discussion sessions proposed
beforehand or on site by participants. I gave one of the keynotes, talking about
the challenges posed and opportunities offered by edge computing. Can share
slides on request, or when I decide on a good way to publish them!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also enjoyed many good discussions and conversations, topped off with a great
BBQ, but two topics stand out. First, a great discussion session organised by
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;anakli.inf.ethz.ch&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Prof. Ana Klimović&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; about serverless computing
which immediately triggered some thoughts about possible followup publications
from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edgeless-project.eu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EDGELESS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and collaboration possibilities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, several conversations on a topic I know little about, low-earth orbit
(LEO) satellite networking, and what could be done with it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, my thought was whether a LEO constellation plus a little
edge compute could provide a difficult-to-disrupt out-of-band monitoring network
for critical infrastructure like datacenters and power grids: although data
bandwidth is limited and a bit complicated due to the constraints on ground
stations, they have pretty decent cameras, so why not use those to capture and
locally process images of the roofs of large rectangular buildings like
datacenters and the like which could continually display various status data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such status information would only need to be locally generated, so it would
take fairly substantial physical disruption of the facility (also presumably
noticeable by camera) to prevent that working. Alternatively, the constellation
(perhaps shared across multiple facilities in different jurisdictions) would
need to be substantially disrupted to prevent it being able to monitor targets.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a fun discussion anyway, combining a network technology I knew little
about with possibly interesting applications of edge computing to resiliency.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Postcript: in case you’re curious, the title is a passing reference to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Star_Trekkin%27&quot;&gt;Star
Trekkin’&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a fine popular music
single from my youth. Which has a much longer back-story on Wikipedia than I had
anticipated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Part II Projects</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/part-ii-projects/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/part-ii-projects/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/part-ii-projects/">&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate final-year (“Part II”) project supervision goes in fits and
starts. After a couple of years of having almost no interest, this year I’ve had
several enquiries and it seems I might end supervising 3–4 projects. So
herewith a record of the things I’ve found myself repeating!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-structure&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#project-structure&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: project-structure&quot;&gt;Project structure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key thing for the structure of the project is to make sure that there is a
core piece that is (essentially) guaranteed to be deliverable. This is the piece
that you know you can do, and once done and written up, you know you can get an
adequate (if not great) mark. Ensuring this takes the risk out of the project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of this core piece, it’s then usually sensible to build “a few” (2? 3?
4?) extensions which will make the project spicy if done well. You may wish to
phrase these extensions as “for example, extensions might include…” or words
to that effect, to give some wiggle room in the final dissertation. Getting
these done successfully is what should put you in line for a very good mark
rather than a simply adequate mark.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-framing&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#project-framing&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: project-framing&quot;&gt;Project framing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also very helpful, particularly if you are aiming for a high mark, to try
to frame the project in terms of &lt;strong&gt;a research question you will answer&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; rather
than &lt;strong&gt;an artefact you will build&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Often in systems the appropriate way to
answer the research questions we pose will be to build an artefact – but by
framing it in terms of the question you seek to answer, it makes it easier to
write the dissertation as a piece of research rather than a &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Small_matter_of_programming&quot;&gt;small matter of
programming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Empirically, this seems to have an outsize effect on the chances of the
examiners thinking the project difficult and marking accordingly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can also be useful to try to be explicit about where your project requires
you to go beyond the CST taught material, particularly from Part IA&#x2F;IB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-proposal&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#project-proposal&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: project-proposal&quot;&gt;Project proposal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my mind there are two critical pieces of the proposal around which everything
else sits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the &lt;strong&gt;evaluation plan&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: if you can write this well, then you understand
what you’re going to build, and what it means to have done it well (or badly).
Writing the evaluation plan therefore usually means you have, for the most part,
got the rest of the project figured out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the &lt;strong&gt;workplan&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: this divides time until submission into two week
(never larger, sometimes smaller) chunks, each of which has attached a &lt;em&gt;calendar
date&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (so there’s no confusion over weeks in term or suchlike) and a
&lt;em&gt;milestone&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x2F;&lt;em&gt;deliverable&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (so that we can immediately tell whether you’ve
completed, or at least are making progress against, that chunk of work in our
weekly meeting). Don’t forget to take account of any relevant module assessment
deadlines in your plan!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it’s a plan not a contract! You don’t lose marks because you deviate
from the plan– but if you can’t tell whether you’re ahead or behind, you might
well find yourself in a sticky position at the end of Lent term or start of
Easter term when you find you’ve got module assessments to complete, revision to
start, two weeks to go until dissertation submission and still four weeks of
work to do on your project…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;supervision-process&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#supervision-process&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: supervision-process&quot;&gt;Supervision process&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I normally supervise projects by scheduling weekly half-hour meetings with each
student. Longer meetings can be arranged on an ad hoc basis as required. The key
purpose of the meeting is to check progress against the workplan, and to make
sure that any difficulties and roadblocks are aired and dealt with (whether in
the meeting or by scheduling a longer discussion).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example of a reasonable target timeline, consider trying to get
implementation completed by the end of Christmas vacation, evaluation completed
by the division of Lent Term, and the dissertation completed by the end of Lent
Term. That then gives you flexibility as to whether you do more project work,
extensions etc., or focus on exam revision, or whatever.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully that’s helpful. At the very least, I can now point potential project
students at it, so it’s helpful for me :) Some of the above may also be relevant
writing research proposals (Part III &#x2F; MPhil projects, even Ph.D.s) but that’s a
topic for another day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Post-COVID19 TPC experience</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/post-covid-tpc/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/post-covid-tpc/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/post-covid-tpc/">&lt;p&gt;I do not participate in a huge number of TPCs (Technical Programme Committees)
as a general rule– partly time constraints but mostly no-one knows who I am so
I don’t often get asked… (!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have done a few though, some big (e.g., &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usenix.org&#x2F;conference&#x2F;nsdi15&quot;&gt;USENIX NSDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;conferences.sigcomm.org&#x2F;imc&#x2F;2018&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ACM IMC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;),
some small (&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;uksystems.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;UK Systems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;link.springer.com&#x2F;conference&#x2F;pam&quot;&gt;PAM&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), and perhaps because I only do
a couple every few years, while doing &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;conferences2.sigcomm.org&#x2F;co-next&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ACM
CoNEXT&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;acm-ieee-sec.org&#x2F;list&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ACM&#x2F;IEEE
SEC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; this week, I found myself particularly
noticing some changes in practice since that last TPCs I recall (notably
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usenix.org&#x2F;conference&#x2F;nsdi15&quot;&gt;NSDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;conferences.sigcomm.org&#x2F;imc&#x2F;2018&#x2F;&quot;&gt;IMC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). So here are three observations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-online-first-and-only&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#1-online-first-and-only&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: 1-online-first-and-only&quot;&gt;1. Online, first and only&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest obvious change is that TPC meetings are now online rather than
in-person. This has one big disadvantage for me: I really enjoyed travelling to
the meeting to meet colleagues and (usually) participate in some TPC-oriented
workshop with presentations of recent an in-progress work. In many ways, I found
this sort of activity more interesting than the conference itself (sorry!). It
also has the unfortunate effect that, at least for international TPCs, timezones
make scheduling tricky – one benefit of travelling was that at least the
meeting took place in localtime for (almost) everyone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it also has clear benefits: the CO2 footprint of the event is
dramatically reduced which can only be a good thing. The financial cost
reduction probably also opens up the experience to attendees who would never
previously have been able to make it. I’ve rarely seen really poor meeting
behaviour on the TPCs I’ve been involved in, but I also find that in an online
meeting, chairing tends to be more easily more rigorous and the sometimes
dominating effect of a single confident (perhaps I might say over-confident, or
even just loud) individual is significantly reduced. Which is good.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-offline-dominance&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#2-offline-dominance&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: 2-offline-dominance&quot;&gt;2. Offline dominance&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now see &lt;strong&gt;dramatically&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; more use being made of commenting and discussions in
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;read.seas.harvard.edu&#x2F;~kohler&#x2F;hotcrp&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HotCRP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which remains the only
conference management and paper reviewing platform I will willingly use (thanks
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Eddie_Kohler&quot;&gt;Eddie&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;!). I don’t know whether this
is a post-pandemic effect, or just the fact that the old old guard has largely
shuffled out of active TPC duties and we now have a new old guard (ie., people
of my era) and younger who are perhaps happier to communicate and express views
without needing to be in the same room.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is another dramatic improvement in process, and puts us in a
similar place to how, for example, we handled marking final year undergraduate
projects at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.nottingham.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Nottingham University&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It means
that discussion is recorded, and usually more coherently and explicitly argued
due to the need to write it down.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-reduction-in-extremism&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#3-reduction-in-extremism&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: 3-reduction-in-extremism&quot;&gt;3. Reduction in extremism&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one arguably slightly negative comment I would have is – and this is only
my anecdotal impression, and not something I can pretend to have data on – that
I think I see a tendency for reviewers to perhaps be a little less clear in
their scoring. Once the across the board strong rejects (a fair number) and
strong accepts (a much smaller number) were taken out, I saw an awful lot of
weak reject (but happy to consider weak accept after discussion) and weak accept
(but happy to consider weak reject after discussion). This made it quite hard
for me, as another reviewer, sometimes to get a clear signal as to what the
other reviews were recommending.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a challenge I sometimes see in admissions interviewing: less experienced
interviewers are sometimes  reluctant to give a clear signal, exhibiting instead
a tendency to score near or perhaps just above the middle of the scale. (I
remember doing this myself.) This feels more comfortable – putting one’s head
above the parapet by taking a clear stance often feels more socially awkward
than giving a “fine, ok, pretty good, sure” response, not least because it needs
stronger supporting argument – but in the end I think it misses the point of
being an interviewer &#x2F; a TPC member which is exactly to accept or reject papers
based on having been recognised for your expertise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the end, two good points, two potential (but minor) negatives, and one
completely unjustifiable and purely selfish negative. Which on the whole is a
good thing. Though having come back to this after a break for a couple of years,
I find I am even more sceptical of the whole process than I was. More later
perhaps, once I get my thoughts in order.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Hosting HotCRP</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/setup-hotcrp/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/setup-hotcrp/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/setup-hotcrp/">&lt;p&gt;I once had cause to setup
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;read.seas.harvard.edu&#x2F;~kohler&#x2F;hotcrp&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HotCRP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for local hosting.
Specifically on a local Lab-hosted VM image.  Some of what follows is specific
to the CUCL VM hosting service, but I think most of it is HotCRP generic and so
may be of use. Anyway, here’s the crib sheet, starting from
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mbtech.github.io&#x2F;Setting-up-hotcrp&#x2F;&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mbtech.github.io&#x2F;Setting-up-hotcrp&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# setup some variables&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-DOMAIN&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;hotcrp-test.cl.cam.ac.uk&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-WORKSHOP&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;sysws18&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-PASSWORD&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;mybestpassword&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-EMAIL&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;postmaster@example.com&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;lab-specifics&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#lab-specifics&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: lab-specifics&quot;&gt;Lab specifics&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume we start from a default Ubuntu template VM, and then…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure the VM&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;cl-asuser&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; passwd&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt; # set UNIX password for sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# create some space&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;for&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; in&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;usr&#x2F;src&#x2F;*&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; ;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; do&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #93A1A1;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;    export&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; K&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;$(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;uname&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -r&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; |&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; sed&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &amp;#39;s&#x2F;-generic$&#x2F;&#x2F;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;    echo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; $K $d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; ...&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;    case&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; $d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; in&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;        &amp;quot;&#x2F;usr&#x2F;src&#x2F;linux-headers-&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;$K&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; |&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &amp;quot;&#x2F;usr&#x2F;src&#x2F;linux-headers-&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;${&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;K&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;-generic&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; )&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;            echo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; keep&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;            ;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;        * )&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;            echo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; remove&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;            sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; rm&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -rf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; $d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;            ;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;    esac&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;done&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# THIS IS UNSAFE! BE CAREFUL! IT CALLS `sudo rm -rf`!&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;for&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; in&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;lib&#x2F;modules&#x2F;*&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; ;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; do&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;    echo $d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; ...&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;    case&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; $d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; in&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;        &amp;quot;&#x2F;lib&#x2F;modules&#x2F;$(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;uname&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -r&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;)&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; )&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;            echo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; keep&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;            ;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;        * )&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;            echo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; remove&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;            sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; rm&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -rf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; $d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;            ;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;    esac&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;done&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# if necessary, resize the partition. this shouldn&amp;#39;t be necessary with the new&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# VM image! if you need more than ~1GB space for papers, setup xvdb1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; fdisk &#x2F;dev&#x2F;xvda&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;p&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;w&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; partprobe&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# resize the default filesystem to use the entire partition&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; resize2fs &#x2F;dev&#x2F;xvda1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt; # blank SIZE means use whole partition&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install packages&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# sort out packages&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #93A1A1;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;export&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; TZ&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;Europe&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;London&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; apt update&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; apt install&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; --no-install-recommends -qq -yy \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    apache2&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    ca-certificates&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    git&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    libapache2-mod-php&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    mailutils&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    mysql-server&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;    php-curl&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    php-json&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    php-mysql&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    poppler-utils&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    postfix&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    zip&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure &lt;code&gt;postfix&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# configure postfix: accept defaults if offered, setup postfix to use ppsw&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; sed&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -i&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &amp;#39;s&#x2F;relayhost =&#x2F;relayhost = ppsw.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&amp;#39; &#x2F;etc&#x2F;postfix&#x2F;main.cf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;etc&#x2F;init.d&#x2F;postfix reload&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; systemctl restart postfix.service&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# test mail sending&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;echo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &amp;quot;Test mail from postfix&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; |&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; mail&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -s&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &amp;quot;Test Postfix&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; ${&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-EMAIL&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more email help, see
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;help.uis.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;email-telephony-and-collaboration&#x2F;email&#x2F;specialist-email-advice&#x2F;sending-email&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;help.uis.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;email-telephony-and-collaboration&#x2F;email&#x2F;specialist-email-advice&#x2F;sending-email&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
using &lt;code&gt;YOUR-DOMAIN&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as mail domain, and &lt;code&gt;ppsw.cam.ac.uk&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as relay host.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install HotCRP&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get latest release:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;git&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; clone https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;kohler&#x2F;hotcrp.git&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;cd&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; hotcrp&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;git&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; checkout tags&#x2F;v2.101&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; v2.101&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup &lt;code&gt;root&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; account for MySQL&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;etc&#x2F;init.d&#x2F;mysql stop&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt; # stop the running service&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# configure and run mysql in the console&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; mkdir&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -p&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;var&#x2F;run&#x2F;mysqld&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; chown mysql:mysql &#x2F;var&#x2F;run&#x2F;mysqld&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; mysqld_safe&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; --skip-grant-tables&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt; sleep&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #D33682;&quot;&gt; 5&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# smash a new `root` password in place &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; mysql&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;ALTER&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; USER &amp;#39;root&amp;#39;@&amp;#39;localhost&amp;#39; IDENTIFIED WITH mysql_native_password BY &amp;#39;${YOUR-PASSWORD}&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;FLUSH&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; PRIVILEGES&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;exit&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# restart mysql properly as a service&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;mysqladmin&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -uroot -p&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;${&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-PASSWORD&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -h127.0.0.1 --protocol=tcp&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; shutdown&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;etc&#x2F;init.d&#x2F;mysql start&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…alternatively&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;mysql&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -uroot&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt;_EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;USE mysql;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;UPDATE mysql.user SET authentication_string = PASSWORD(&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;${&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-PASSWORD&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;WHERE User = &amp;#39;root&amp;#39; AND Host = &amp;#39;localhost&amp;#39;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;FLUSH PRIVILEGES;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;QUIT&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt;_EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secure your MySQL installation&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; systemctl stop mysql&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; mkdir&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -p&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;var&#x2F;run&#x2F;mysqld&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; chown mysql:mysql &#x2F;var&#x2F;run&#x2F;mysqld&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; mysqld_safe&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; --skip-grant-tables --skip-networking&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; mysql_secure_installation&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -p&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;${&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-PASSWORD&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;}&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt;EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;y&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;y&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;y&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;y&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt;EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;7&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup the HotCRP MySQL tables and config&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;lib&#x2F;createdb.sh&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; --user=root --password=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;${&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;YOUR-PASSWORD&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;} &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;ok&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;YOUR-WORKSHOP&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# edit conf&#x2F;options.php&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# - contactName&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# - contactEmail&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# - sendEmail&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# - emailFrom&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# - emailSender&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# - timezone&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# - upload_max_filesize [ if you care ]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;8&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn on the HotCRP site in your Apache configuration&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #586E75;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# apache2: turn on hotcrp site&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; sh&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -c&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &amp;#39;cat &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&#x2F;etc&#x2F;apache2&#x2F;conf-available&#x2F;hotcrp.conf &amp;lt;&amp;lt;_EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;Directory &amp;quot;$(pwd -P)&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    Options Indexes Includes FollowSymLinks&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    AllowOverride all&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;    Require all granted&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&#x2F;Directory&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;Alias &#x2F;YOUR-WORKSHOP $(pwd -P)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;_EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; a2enconf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;hotcrp&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;EOF&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; chgrp www-data conf&#x2F;options.php&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; service apache2 reload&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; apache2ctl graceful&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…and you should now be able to access your hotcrp site at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;$%7BYOUR-DOMAIN%7D&#x2F;$%7BYOUR-WORKSHOP%7D&quot;&gt;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;${YOUR-DOMAIN}&#x2F;${YOUR-WORKSHOP}&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;9&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;letsencrypt.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Let’s Encrypt&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to create and configure
certificates for HTTPS support&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; apt install&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -yy&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; software-properties-common&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; add-apt-repository ppa:certbot&#x2F;certbot&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; apt update&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; apt install&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -yy&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; certbot-auto&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;wget&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; https:&#x2F;&#x2F;dl.eff.org&#x2F;certbot-auto&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;chmod&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; a+x .&#x2F;certbot-auto&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; .&#x2F;certbot-auto&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -n --os-packages-only&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; .&#x2F;certbot-auto&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -a&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; webroot&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -i&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; apache&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -w&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; $(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;pwd&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; -P&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt;     --agree-tos --redirect --uir --hsts --staple-ocsp \&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt;     -d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; YOUR-DOMAIN&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; --email&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; YOUR-EMAIL&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; .&#x2F;certbot-auto&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #CB4B16;&quot;&gt; --install-only&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;&lt;!--
sudo apt install snapd
sudo snap install core; sudo snap refresh core
sudo snap install --classic certbot
sudo ln -s &#x2F;snap&#x2F;bin&#x2F;certbot &#x2F;usr&#x2F;bin&#x2F;certbot

sudo certbot --apache
## follow prompts
--&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;10&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set permissions on the certificate directories&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; chgrp www-data &#x2F;etc&#x2F;letsencrypt&#x2F;live&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; chmod g+rx &#x2F;etc&#x2F;letsencrypt&#x2F;live&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; chgrp www-data &#x2F;etc&#x2F;letsencrypt&#x2F;archive&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; chmod g+rx &#x2F;etc&#x2F;letsencrypt&#x2F;archive&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End state is the Apache config looks something like the following, with
unindented lines being those I added:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;shellscript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; cat &#x2F;etc&#x2F;apache2&#x2F;sites-available&#x2F;hotcrp.conf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;IfModule mod_ssl.c&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;SSLStaplingCache&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; shmcb:&#x2F;var&#x2F;run&#x2F;apache2&#x2F;stapling_cache&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;128000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;	&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;VirtualHost&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; _default_:44&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;3&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;		ServerAdmin&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; webmaster@localhost&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;		DocumentRoot&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;home&#x2F;hotcrp&#x2F;hotcrp&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;		ErrorLog&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; ${&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;APACHE_LOG_DIR&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;error.log&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;		CustomLog&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt; ${&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;APACHE_LOG_DIR&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;access.log combined&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;		SSLEngine&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; on&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;SSLCACertificateFile&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;etc&#x2F;letsencrypt&#x2F;live&#x2F;hotcrp.sysws.org.uk&#x2F;fullchain.pem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;SSLUseStapling&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; on&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;		&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;FilesMatch&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &amp;quot;\.(cgi|shtml|phtml|php)$&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;				SSLOptions&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; +StdEnvVars&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;		&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;FilesMatch&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;		&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;Directory&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;usr&#x2F;lib&#x2F;cgi-bi&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;				SSLOptions&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; +StdEnvVars&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;		&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;Directory&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;ServerName&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; hotcrp.sysws.org.uk&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;SSLCertificateFile&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;etc&#x2F;letsencrypt&#x2F;live&#x2F;hotcrp.sysws.org.uk-0001&#x2F;fullchain.pem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;SSLCertificateKeyFile&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;etc&#x2F;letsencrypt&#x2F;live&#x2F;hotcrp.sysws.org.uk-0001&#x2F;privkey.pem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;Include&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; &#x2F;etc&#x2F;letsencrypt&#x2F;options-ssl-apache.conf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;Header&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; always set Strict-Transport-Security &amp;quot;max-age=31536000&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;Header&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; always set Content-Security-Policy upgrade-insecure-requests&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;	&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;VirtualHost&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#x2F;IfModule&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;11.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; Add DNS entry for the name assigned&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; (in&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt; my case, `&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;hotcrp.DOMAIN&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #2AA198;&quot;&gt;`&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Zen and the Art of Research Management</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/zen-and-the-art-of-research-management/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/zen-and-the-art-of-research-management/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/zen-and-the-art-of-research-management/">&lt;p&gt;I think this is a bit of a classic, the first written form of which I came
across in &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;misc&#x2F;obituaries&#x2F;needham&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Prof. Roger Needham&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;’s &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;events&#x2F;50+5&#x2F;&quot;&gt;50+5 Festschrift&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; celebrating his
time at the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cambridge University Computer Lab&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;research&#x2F;lab&#x2F;microsoft-research-cambridge&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Microsoft Research Cambridge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I don’t know who originated it, but the
copy there is certainly due to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;memex.naughtons.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;John Naughton&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Robert_Taylor_(computer_scientist)&quot;&gt;Bob Taylor&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I
suppose one might quibble point 12, in that I seem to recall Roger did a lot of
pacing about, but a good chair is certainly a worthwhile thing to provide.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I find myself wanting to point at it from time-to-time, so here it is!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;memex.naughtons.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;John Naughton&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Open University, Milton Keynes, England&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;), and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Robert_Taylor_(computer_scientist)&quot;&gt;Robert
W. Taylor&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Woodside, California, USA&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HIRE ONLY THE VERY BEST PEOPLE, EVEN IF THEY ARE CUSSED. Perhaps especially
if they are cussed. Your guiding principle should be to employ people who
are smarter than you. One superb researcher is worth dozens of merely good
ones.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ONCE YOU’VE GOT THEM, TRUST THEM. Do not attempt to micro-manage talented
people. (Remember rule #1.) Set broad goals and leave them to it.
Concentrate your own efforts on strategy and nurturing the environment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PROTECT YOUR RESEARCHERS FROM EXTERNAL INTERFERENCE, whether from company
personnel officers, senior executives or security personnel. Remember that
your job is to create a supportive and protective space within which they
can work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MUCH OF WHAT YOU DO WILL FALL INTO THE CATEGORY OF ABSORBING THE UNCERTAINTY
OF YOUR RESEARCHERS.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REMEMBER THAT YOU ARE A CONDUCTOR, NOT A SOLOIST. (Rule #1 again.) The Lab
is your performance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DO NOT PAY TOO MUCH ATTENTION TO ‘RELEVANCE,’ ‘DELIVERABLES’ and other
concepts beloved of Senior Management.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REMEMBER THAT CREATIVE PEOPLE ARE LIKE HEARTS – they go where they are
appreciated. They can be inspired or led, but not managed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KEEP THE ORGANISATION CHART SHALLOW. Never let the Lab grow beyond the point
where you cannot fit everyone comfortably in the same room.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MAKE YOUR RESEARCHERS DEBATE WITH ONE ANOTHER REGULARLY. Let them tear one
another’s ideas to pieces. Ensure frank communication among them. Observe
the strengths and weaknesses which emerge in the process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BE NICE TO GRADUATE STUDENTS. One day they may keep you, even if only as a
mascot. (Moreover, they are a lot of fun!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INSTALL A WORLD-CLASS COFFEE MACHINE and provide plenty of free soft drinks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BUY AERON CHAIRS. Remember that most computer science research is done
sitting down.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INSTITUTE A ‘TOY BUDGET’, enabling anyone in the Lab to buy anything costing
less than a specified amount on their own authority. And provide a darkened
recovery room for accountants shocked by the discovery of this budget.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PAY ATTENTION TO WHAT GOES ON IN UNIVERSITIES. Every significant
breakthrough in computing in the last four decades has involved both the
university and corporate sectors at some point in its evolution.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REMEMBER TO INITIATE AND SPONSOR CELEBRATIONS when merited.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHEN IN DOUBT, ASK YOURSELF: “WHAT WOULD ROGER NEEDHAM DO IN SIMILAR
CIRCUMSTANCES?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Fame and Fortune!</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/bigtechday-mirage/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/bigtechday-mirage/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/bigtechday-mirage/">&lt;p&gt;After a slew of HDI related items, a quick &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;openmirage.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MirageOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; note. I was invited to
give a presentation on MirageOS at the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tngtech.com&#x2F;en.html&quot;&gt;TNG&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tngtech.com&#x2F;en&#x2F;big-techday.html&quot;&gt;Big TechDay 8&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; conference. This
was an interesting, and very broad based, event. It brought together about 500
people with about 25 speakers over one day, on topics from cognitive science to
AI to chess playing algorithms to obviating testing through proof reasoning.
And, of course, operating systems and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;openmirage.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MirageOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;! If you’re interested, the
slides used are available at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;decks.openmirage.org&#x2F;bigtechday8&quot;&gt;decks.openmirage.org&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in the usual
way, and if you really want to hear me droning on, TNG are making the video
(with synchronised slides)
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.techcast.com&#x2F;events&#x2F;bigtechday8&#x2F;salvator-1130&#x2F;?q=salvator-1130&quot;&gt;available&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As ever, comments welcome!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Actual HCI Papers!</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/ecscw-and-aarhus/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/ecscw-and-aarhus/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/ecscw-and-aarhus/">&lt;p&gt;I have to confess to being quite pleased to having a couple of
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hdiresearch.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;-related papers accepted recently (even if we
can’t even get proper reviews on the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;ssrn.com&#x2F;abstract=2508051&quot;&gt;original HDI paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; – recently judged
out-of-scope for the third time, even though the Special Issue in question
seemed bang on target!).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is a full paper to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ecscw2015.no&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ECSCW’15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; titled
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mor1.github.io&#x2F;publications&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;ecscw15-hdi.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Human Data Interaction: Historical Lessons from Social Studies and CSCW&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
A collaboration with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.andy-crabtree.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dr Andy Crabtree&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, it
examines particularly the role of &lt;em&gt;interaction&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in HDI and explores how past
technical approaches, such as
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mor1.github.io&#x2F;publications&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;comsnets11-dataware.pdf&quot;&gt;Dataware&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, to
the challenges posed by HDI haven’t fully considered the inherently social
nature of data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is a short paper to the decennial – seriously: every ten years! –
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;aarhus2015.org&quot;&gt;Aarhus 2015&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; conference titled
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mor1.github.io&#x2F;publications&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;aarhus15-databox.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Personal Data: Thinking Inside the Box&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
This sets out a vision for an embodiment of a &lt;em&gt;Databox&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: a physical device
supported by online services that empowers us to take back control of our online
lives. Building a Databox, using &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mirage.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MirageOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, is hopefully
going to be a key activity for me in the coming months…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Taking it to the People People</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/hdi-seminar/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/hdi-seminar/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/hdi-seminar/">&lt;p&gt;Looks like I get a chance to run my mouth off again :) Upcoming
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hdiresearch.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.crassh.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;events&#x2F;26198&quot;&gt;research
seminar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, organised by &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.bigdata.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cambridge Big
Data&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x2F;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.digitalhumanities.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Digital
Humanities&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. In short, details are:
&lt;strong&gt;20th April 2015, 14:00–16:00&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;S1, Alison Richard Building, West Road,
Cambridge&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. If you’d like to attend, please do register at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.eventbrite.co.uk&#x2F;e&#x2F;human-data-interaction-cambridge-big-datadigital-humanities-seminar-tickets-16337148852&quot;&gt;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.eventbrite.co.uk&#x2F;e&#x2F;human-data-interaction-cambridge-big-datadigital-humanities-seminar-tickets-16337148852&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just because pixels are, in some loose sense, nearly free, here’s the
abstract from the seminar link above:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increasing generation and collection of personal data has created a
complex ecosystem, often collaborative but sometimes combative, around
companies and individuals engaging in the use of these data. We propose that
the interactions between these agents warrant a new topic of study: Human-Data
Interaction (HDI), that sits at the intersection of various disciplines,
including computer science, statistics, sociology, psychology and behavioural
economics._&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this brief presentation I will pose some of the challenges that HDI raises,
organised into three core themes of legibility, agency and negotiability. I
will also outline some of the technical work we are currently undertaking that
attempts to address some of the underlying platform problems. My hope is to
elicit discussion of both the HDI framework and the technical solutions we are
pursuing, as well as to engage in a broader conversation about the ways we
should approach the personal data ecosystem with other interested parties._&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>I Think Someone Else Is Also Following Me...</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/being-followed-postscript/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/being-followed-postscript/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/being-followed-postscript/">&lt;p&gt;Turns out others were listening too – notably the USA’s &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.darpa.mil&#x2F;&quot;&gt;DARPA&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The recent
announcement of the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.darpa.mil&#x2F;NewsEvents&#x2F;Releases&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;11.aspx&quot;&gt;Brandeis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; programme makes explicit reference to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;ssrn.com&#x2F;abstract=2508051&quot;&gt;HDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hdiresearch.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;our website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. This has been picked up by &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;gcn.com&#x2F;articles&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;12&#x2F;darpa-brandeis.aspx&quot;&gt;GCN&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usatoday.com&#x2F;story&#x2F;nation&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;16&#x2F;data-privacy-darpa-brandeis&#x2F;70222556&#x2F;&quot;&gt;USAToday&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.nbcnews.com&#x2F;tech&#x2F;security&#x2F;darpa-unexpectedly-announces-program-improve-online-piracy-n322601&quot;&gt;NBCNews&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.engadget.com&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;12&#x2F;darpa-is-trying-to-reinvent-online-privacy&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Engadget&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; among others. With $60M potentially on the table, I
hope that there’ll be many more who get interested in pushing HDI forwards now
:)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>I Think Someone&#x27;s Following Me...</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/someones-following-me/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/someones-following-me/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/someones-following-me/">&lt;p&gt;It’s always&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; nice when someone notices what you’re doing, and I was
pleasantly surprised recently to find that someone had indeed been watching.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-2-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, it appears that someone at MIT Technology Review has noticed the
work of me and some of my pals: our work on &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;2015&#x2F;01&#x2F;05&#x2F;169715&#x2F;the-emerging-science-of-human-data-interaction&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and a recent sketch of some
follow-on work we’re pursuing around building a personal &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;2015&#x2F;01&#x2F;26&#x2F;169495&#x2F;how-a-box-could-solve-the-personal-data-conundrum&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Databox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Independently of that, the latter also happened to get picked up by
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theguardian.com&#x2F;profile&#x2F;johnnaughton&quot;&gt;John Naughton&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theguardian.com&#x2F;technology&#x2F;2015&#x2F;feb&#x2F;01&#x2F;control-personal-data-databox-end-user-agreement&quot;&gt;Guardian&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which ended up with a pretty
active comments thread, including one from Richard Stallman himself…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guess we’d better get on and deliver it now then :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, usually. Unless you’re doing something embarrassing like, e.g.,
dancing. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though in fact, given the pattern involved, I suspect it may be my
colleague, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk&#x2F;~hamed&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dr Hamed Haddadi&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; who’s
actually being followed. To whit, the fact that they also picked up on &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;2014&#x2F;09&#x2F;12&#x2F;171400&#x2F;the-murky-world-of-third-party-web-tracking&#x2F;&quot;&gt;a
study&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
of third-party web-tracking from last year. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-2-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Talks, Old and New</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/talks-old-and-new/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/talks-old-and-new/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/talks-old-and-new/">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to an invitation from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;um&#x2F;people&#x2F;hiballan&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Hitesh&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I recently got the chance to revisit my
old stomping ground at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;labs&#x2F;cambridge&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Microsoft Research Cambridge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Well, I say “old”
– in the intervening 7 years, they’ve moved to a rather splendid new building
at the other end of Cambridge, just next to the station. (And improved the
coffee too, not that it wasn’t pretty good to start with!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this was a pleasant chance to catch up with some old colleagues, meet
some new ones, and even speak to my most recently graduated Ph.D. student,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;people&#x2F;a-ewluge&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dr Ewa Luger&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; – and who’d’ve thought that I’d ever end up supervising
someone coming from the discipline of Political Science too!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ostensible reason was to talk about the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;homenetworks.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Homework&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; project – a talk I’ve
given a &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=AdtVSrazVaQ&quot;&gt;few times now&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; – and to lead from that into discussing some
of my current agenda, around &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hdiresearch.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Human-Data Interaction&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mort.io&#x2F;research&#x2F;&quot;&gt;User-Centred Systems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It seemed to go pretty well – a few
questions, and some lively discussion over lunch followed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happily, the fine folk at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;labs&#x2F;cambridge&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MSRC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; recorded it and have made it available, so if
you’re really interested, you can take a look – direct your browser of choice to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;apps&#x2F;video&#x2F;default.aspx?id=238157&quot;&gt;Interacting with Infrastructure: Home Networking and Beyond&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say, when I checked that link in the course of writing this, one thing
that did come as something of a surprise was to notice that a talk I didn’t
remember giving – it was 8 years ago to be fair! – is also available. So if
you’ve a burning desire to find out about
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;apps&#x2F;video&#x2F;default.aspx?id=104278&quot;&gt;Measuring and Monitoring Microsoft’s Enterprise Network&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
it turns out you can do that too. The past haunts us they say. In my case, it
seems that the haunting has happened already, and turned my hair mostly white in
the process… :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
