<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>mort’s mythopœia - research</title>
    <subtitle>with apologies</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://mort.io/tags/research/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mort.io/tags/research/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Systematising the obvious</title>
        <published>2025-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/research-matrix/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/research-matrix/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/research-matrix/">&lt;p&gt;Ok, so this is one of those that comes about because I found myself saying the
same thing to different people a couple of times within a week or so. Which I
usually think means I should probably write it down.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been talking with Ph.D. students about selecting research topics, doing
research, and what is interesting subsequently to report in papers. In doing so
I recalled some advice that was given to me during my Ph.D. — so I’m not taking
credit for this, though I can’t recall who specifically said it to me like this
first; possibly Ralph Becket. What follows is of course scoped to computer
systems research as far as I’m concerned, though it may well apply more broadly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;figure class=&quot;fi fr pd1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;research-matrix.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A plain whiteboard sketch of the matrix described in the main text&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A whiteboard sketch of the obvious&#x2F;successful matrix.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, to the point. I have sometimes found it useful to think about research
topics and their results as placed along two axes, each of which I split into
two categories. The first axis might be labelled &lt;em&gt;obviousness&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with the two
categories labelled “&lt;em&gt;obviously…&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;” and “&lt;em&gt;non-obviously…&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;”.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; The second
axis might be labelled &lt;em&gt;success&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with the two categories “&lt;em&gt;…works&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;” and
“&lt;em&gt;…doesn’t work&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;”. Finally, I put an indicator in each quadrant as to the
desirability of work in that quadrant – shown in the picture as ticks (the more
ticks, the more desirable), or crosses (undesirable).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering each of the quadrants then, we have in order of desirability:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;non-obviously works&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Bingo! This is when you’ve done something that
people didn’t think would work but it turns out you had sufficient insight,
skill, luck, resources, or whatever to make it work. Reporting this sort of
work is happy times – fame, glory, riches, the prize. No, wait, that’s not
right. Oh yes — you get a good published paper. Nice.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;obviously works&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: The bulk of published research in my experience.
Certainly not bad, and definitely contributing to knowledge. But not really
surprising — unlikely to create that elusive “wow! that’s cool!” feeling.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;non-obviously doesn’t work&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Far too little of this sort of thing is
published in my opinion. I feel quite pleased when I manage work like this
because I don’t need to care quite so much as I used to about getting papers
accepted and I find the process and outcome interesting. But it is sometimes
hard to get this work out there as it often seems too easy for reviewers to
focus on the fact the thing didn’t work rather than considering the
contribution you’ve made by showing that everyone else’s intuitions are
wrong. Sad but mildly self-righteous times ensue.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;obviously doesn’t work&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: No-one cares. Tends to get a big “yeah? and?
idiot” from reviewers. I wouldn’t usually bother except as a personal
learning exercise.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I realise that the more natural word here would have been
&lt;em&gt;surprisingly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Sigh. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Rewarding influence</title>
        <published>2025-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;2025.eurosys.org&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;EuroSys 2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; was co-located with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; this year. Other
commitments meant I (again) couldn’t stay for the whole conference, attending
primarily because &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;tdis-accepted&#x2F;&quot;&gt;two students had papers in the TDIS
workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&quot;stage.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of me in a yellow t-shirt receiving the award&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But happily I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; able to stay for the first day of the conference –
“happily” not only because it gave me a chance to catch up with some old friends
I hadn’t seen in a decade or more, but also because &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;2451116.2451167&quot;&gt;the Mirage unikernels
paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which appeared at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;asplos13.rice.edu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2013&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; won one of two &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&#x2F;awards&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS 2025 Influential Papers
awards&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is obviously very flattering – typically doing research is necessarily its
own reward because the work can seem fruitless much of the time. Even when a
paper gets written and submitted it will most likely be rejected – I think
EuroSys this year reported something like a 12% acceptance rate, so rejection is
&lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the most likely outcome. Finally, if the paper does finally get
accepted, it will most likely sink without trace – perhaps a brief flurry of
interest for a few months or so, the paper gets cited a few times, and then it
fades away. This seems inevitable in a reasonably fast moving field that is also
growing at pace – EuroSys had ~160 attendees in 2006, growing to ~330 in the 10
years to 2016, but hitting ~1100 this year; while submissions grew from ~200 in
2019 to 696 this year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&quot;official.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of the certificate&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to win an award recognising that others feel a paper actually had some
influence is rare, and makes me very happy :) At the same time, it reinforces a
couple of lessons that I really should’ve internalised by now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is that papers inevitably get better for thoughtful considered
feedback from experts a step or several away from the work – so drafts should
be produced in plenty of time and distributed to anyone who’s willing to take
the time for feedback. In the case of this paper the previous failed submission
to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usenix.org&#x2F;conference&#x2F;osdi12&quot;&gt;OSDI 2012&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; had, let’s say, reviews
of mixed quality. But one stood out, from Jon Howell (who signs his reviews so I
know it was him), who gave us a firm “reject” which (in retrospect) was actually
fairly well-deserved but in an incredibly constructive way. To paraphrase him
slightly, the work was interesting but the paper was crap – &lt;em&gt;and here’s how to
rewrite it so it makes sense&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. We basically did what he said, ASPLOS accepted
it, and the rest is now history. (Over a decade ago, good grief.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is that I simply cannot predict whether any research I’m doing is
actually going to turn out to have any value. The only other equivalent award
I’ve had was an &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;infocom2024.ieee-infocom.org&#x2F;awards&quot;&gt;INFOCOM 2024 Test of Time
award&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1109&#x2F;INFCOM.2012.6195845&quot;&gt;our 2012 paper on a
system called &lt;em&gt;Thinkair&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, about
mobile-code offload from devices to the cloud. That paper had received
considerably more than just one rejection prior to acceptance, and if I recall
my final contribution correctly, I recommended not submitting it to INFOCOM as I
didn’t think we’d done enough to address previous review comments.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shows what I know. But then, how boring would life be without a little
ignorance… :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Not one but two accepted papers and a Ph.D.</title>
        <published>2025-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/">&lt;p&gt;As I find myself once more on a train to parts unknown (to me at least), a brief
update :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parts unknown in question is Rotterdam, NL (so really quite well-known to
quite a lot of people, just not me) for &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;2025.eurosys.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EURO&#x2F;SYS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (being held jointly with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, although I can’t stay for
the whole thing unfortunately) and specifically the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tdis.gitlab.io&#x2F;tdis25&#x2F;&quot;&gt;3rd International Workshop
of Testing Distributed Internet of Things Systems
(TDIS)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Happily the programme committee decided to accept two papers from my
(ex-)students – which is nice :) The two in question are&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3719159.3721222&quot;&gt;Reckon-ing Kubernetes at the Edge using Emulated
Clusters&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; with Alessandro Sassi
(University of Cambridge &#x2F; Politecnico di Milano) and Christopher Jensen
(University of Cambridge &#x2F; Microsoft Research). This describes Alessandro’s
M.Sc. research project undertaken as a visitor with my group. He built on
Chris’ earlier work on &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3447851.3458739&quot;&gt;Reckon, an emulator setup for examining consensus
system behaviour&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Alessandor
extended this to use ContainerNet enabling it to emulate Kubernetes clusters
on a single node, and used this to examine Kubernetes performance in some
edge network scenarios. Source available on GitHub at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;AleSassi&#x2F;reckon-k8s&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;AleSassi&#x2F;reckon-k8s&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3719159.3721221&quot;&gt;LoRaLive: Efficient LoRaWAN Traffic
Generation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; with Vadim Safronov
(University of Oxford &#x2F; University of Cambridge). This reports a component of
Vadim’s Ph.D. work where he built a system to enable dense deployment LoRaWAN
trace-playback using a minimal number of nodes while respecting legal
constraints on duty cycles. Source available on GitHub at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;LoRaLive&#x2F;LoRaLive&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;LoRaLive&#x2F;LoRaLive&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both nice tools that we hope might be of community interest!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ph.D. in question is Chris Jensen’s – happily he passed his viva on
Thursday just gone, titled “Separating conflict-recovery from failure-recovery
in distributed consensus”, examined by &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;timharris.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tim Harris&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;charap.co&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Aleksey Charapko&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Other recent passes include Al-Amjad
Tawfiq Isstaif, titled “Contention-resilient overcommitment for serverless
deployments” and Andrew Jeffery, titled “Modelling orchestration”. The race&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
is now on for the first to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;techreports&#x2F;&quot;&gt;tech
report&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not really a race. That would be weird. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>PhD viva, UK style</title>
        <published>2025-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/">&lt;p&gt;Having recently, happily, had several PhD students completing in short order,
I’ve been approaching external PhD examiners. Occasionally I find myself asking
someone who’s not done any &#x2F; many in the UK previously. As our system – as all
such systems! – is a bit different to those in other parts of the world, I’ve
written a few notes on a couple of occasions about what to expect. So I figured
I might as well publish them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is my impression &#x2F; understanding based on experience here in the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cst.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Department of Computer Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cambridge University&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; ca. 2025. Your Mileage May Vary
anywhen and anywhere else, including anywhere else in the UK – check local
regulations to be sure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of process, the system here is that candidates submit their complete
dissertation and then undergo a “viva voce” (oral examination). It would be
usual for the viva to take place within 2—3 months of submission. It’s better
(IMO, much better) if it can happen in person but we may still be able to
arrange to do it online in extremis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two examiners:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;internal examiner&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (typically connected to the Department) who ensures
the process is followed properly but may not be a deep expert in the specific
topic, and&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;external examiner&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (from outside the University) who is there as the
subject matter expert.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The viva consists of the two examiners asking the candidate questions about
their dissertation until they’re satisfied; typically this takes at least 2h and
can go longer, though more than 3.5—4h is unusual in my experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examiners are each expected to read the dissertation in detail before the
viva and each write a short (typically 1—2pp) independent report giving their
opinion, outlining any concerns they will have and the resulting
topics&#x2F;questions they will be exploring in the viva, and indicating what their a
priori judgement is in terms of recommendation (roughly: pass&#x2F;pass with
corrections&#x2F;revise &amp;amp; resubmit&#x2F;no Ph.D. but you can have a Masters&#x2F;fail).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examiners will then typically meet ~30min or so before the viva to discuss
their independent reports and decide on the approach to take in the viva. After
the viva they write a joint report (usually shorter than their independent
reports; perhaps 0.5pp) outlining what happened in the viva, as well as making a
final recommendation and providing (if appropriate) a list of corrections that
must be satisfied for the candidate to pass.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the University pays a (risibly small) honorarium to the external
examiner for doing the viva plus reasonable expenses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Fontsizing in LaTeX</title>
        <published>2025-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/fontsizing/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/fontsizing/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/fontsizing/">&lt;p&gt;I recently had colleagues hit an issue that I have hit myself in the past, and
so I finally decided to figure out a fix.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, when building EPSRC research proposals in LaTeX, getting a
complaint that the font size is non compliant – it should be 11pt Arial, but
the standard LaTeX options generate something slightly smaller, with Adobe
Acrobat and Microsoft tools both reporting a size of 10.45pt or so.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One proposed solution was the to add the following in the preamble:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;anyfontsize&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\AtBeginDocument&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\fontsize&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{11bp}{13.35bp}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\selectfont&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;} &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…but that did not work unfortunately.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some poking about and staring at output and searching the interwebs, it
appears that this was triggered, at least for me, by the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ctan.org&#x2F;pkg&#x2F;fontspec&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;fontspec&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; package that was being used to sort
out fonts and unicode and so on in conjunction with
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;xetex.sourceforge.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;XeLaTeX&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as a backend driver.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key piece of debug logic was to add the following text in a document:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;The quick fox --- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\the\fontdimen&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;6&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\font\relax&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…which ensured there was some text and then inserted the font dimesions
according to LaTeX. It did indeed produce the output &lt;code&gt;The quick fox — 9.54147pt&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; when it should’ve been &lt;code&gt;10pt&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The font runes I was using were&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[T1]{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;fontenc&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;lmodern&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;amssymb,amsmath&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;eurosym&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;upquote&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;microtype&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;fontspec&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;xltxtra,xunicode&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\defaultfontfeatures&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{Mapping=tex-text,Scale=MatchUppercase}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #93A1A1;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;\renewcommand&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\familydefault&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\rmdefault&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\setmainfont&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{Arial}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\setmonofont&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{Hack Nerd Font}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…and it seemed to be the &lt;code&gt;Scale=MatchUppercase&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; clause that caused the
problem. Further investigation suggested that most of that was actually
copypasta legacy code that was no longer required; replacing with&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #839496; background-color: #002B36;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;\usepackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #859900;&quot;&gt;fontspec&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\setmainfont&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{Arial}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #268BD2;&quot;&gt;\setmonofont&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{Hack Nerd Font}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…gave the output &lt;code&gt;The quick fox — 10.0pt&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; in Arial as expected. Which was
nice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also realised in the course of doing this that &lt;code&gt;xelatex&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is now deprecated as
a backend, so I have started using the still actively developed
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.luatex.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;luatex&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; backend driver instead by passing
&lt;code&gt;-lualatex&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mgeier.github.io&#x2F;latexmk.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;latexmk&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and that has
worked fine so far&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Introducing `bibtox`</title>
        <published>2025-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/bibtox/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/bibtox/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/bibtox/">&lt;p&gt;After some time using various tools and scripts to format and sort my files of
BibTeX&#x2F;BibLaTeX entries, I finally gave up back in March and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;bibtox&quot;&gt;wrote one myself
– &lt;code&gt;bibtox&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. This replaced some very nasty
combination of server-side &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;bibtox&#x2F;blob&#x2F;83eda34bc9e79bd5251b1ae9623b5e905532c599&#x2F;bib2json.py&quot;&gt;Python&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and in-page &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;bibtox&#x2F;blob&#x2F;83eda34bc9e79bd5251b1ae9623b5e905532c599&#x2F;papers.coffee&quot;&gt;CoffeeScript&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, plus a
third-party tool &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;backtracking&#x2F;bibtex2html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bib2bib&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; I
would run on an ad hoc basis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;bibtox&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;README.md&quot;&gt;README&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, this
processes either a stream of entries on &lt;code&gt;stdin&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or a set of files arranged into
sections specified by a simple configuration file. It outputs sorted or
unsorted, either as canonicalised entries or marked up HTML.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it means that, hopefully, finally, my list of publications on this site is
consistently formatted and sorted. Completeness is, of course, a process rather
than a state so achieving that is left for other times and places.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;bibtox&#x2F;issues&quot;&gt;Issues&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;bibtox&#x2F;pulls&quot;&gt;pull
requests&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; welcome!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Retreat from TUM</title>
        <published>2024-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/tum-retreat/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/tum-retreat/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/tum-retreat/">&lt;p&gt;Ok, ok, I exaggerate – it’s not really that far. But any time I have to set the
alarm for 02.30, it feels like it’s a long long way away!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;research-group&#x2F;&quot;&gt;TU Munchen&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; host an &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;events&#x2F;mir3&#x2F;&quot;&gt;annual
retreat&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and thanks to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;research-group&#x2F;joerg-ott&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Prof. Joerg
Ott&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; I was invited this
year for the first time. It’s held in TUM’s &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.raitenhaslach.tum.de&#x2F;en&#x2F;raitenhaslach&#x2F;home&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Retreat Centre at
Raitenhaslach&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
originally a Cistercian monastery which is a lovely location except that it’s a
bus ride from the hotel used and a bus and three trains from the nearest airport
– which is, mildly confusingly,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.salzburg-airport.com&#x2F;en&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Salzburg&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; not
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.munich-airport.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Munich&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The latter point made me assume that
there would be good directions via public transport from Salzburg, but that
turned out not to be the case. And as Google Maps is, at best, patchy in terms
of public transport coverage in this part of the world – it doesn’t know about
all the buses at least – I thought it might be useful to record the process of
getting there from Cambridge.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;events&#x2F;mir3&#x2F;mir3-2024-10&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;photo.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of the presenter in next to a slide in an ornately
    decorated room&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, to fly to Salzburg or Munich? In the end I picked Salzburg as it was
closer to the retreat centre itself and meant I didn’t need to fly via Heathrow
or Gatwick. As I had to be in Cambridge the night before for family reasons,
picking a closer airport for my very early flight seemed sensible. Unfortunately
this means flying Wizzair UK from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.london-luton.co.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;London Luton
Airport&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which after just twice flying from
there remains my least favourite UK airport. Given the flight departed at 05.55,
a £77.50 taxi from Cambridge was the only option.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per Panther’s recommmendation I allowed 70 minutes for the journey, and on my
own recommendation I aimed to arrive ~1.5h before the flight resulting in a taxi
booking for 03.15. Happily when I get in the taxi the driver said it would be
around 45-50 minutes, which was nice. Less happily when I checked in the day
before – using a laptop as neither Safari nor Firefox on iOS was able to
display the boarding pass – I got an automatic email from Wizzair telling me
that I needed to arrive at the airport by 02.15 as the airport was upgrading
their “central search facilities”. After trying to call the airport half a dozen
times but getting trapped in the IVR menus at the inevitable “read the FAQ on
the website” end state, I gave up trying to check if that really was necessary
and decided to risk my original timings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did however spot one useful thing: “prebooked security check”. This appears to
be the ability to book, at 15 minute granularity, a security check during peak
hours (03.00-04.30). Given my estimated arrival time of 04.15, that seemed
perfect.
 &lt;img src=&quot;road.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of a road being worked&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;

As it was also &lt;strong&gt;completely free&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; requiring nothing more than my
flight number and an email address (not even the one associated with my ticket),
I booked it resulting in an email with a QR code to show to security. This
worked perfectly when I arrived at the airport: show the person on security the
QR code on the phone screen, and they simply jump you past the security queue to
the front. Did I mention this was completely free? Seems a strange system to me
but hey, I’ll take it!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, the public transport worked though there was a short walk at the end
that was longer than I expected – rebuilding a road meant I could get through
but the bus couldn’t! And then the retreat happened – but you can &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;events&#x2F;mir3&#x2F;mir3-2024-10&#x2F;&quot;&gt;read about
that elsewhere&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Workshopping, across the universe</title>
        <published>2024-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/workshopping-edgeless/">&lt;p&gt;One of the pleasures of being an academic is to travel to nice places to meet
interesting people, and interesting places to meet nice people. In one of my
first such trips for a few years I recently went to Sweden to participate in the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;17th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;17th Cloud Control Workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;17th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;photo.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of the presenter in front of a slide&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d previously attended the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloudresearch.org&#x2F;workshops&#x2F;15th&#x2F;&quot;&gt;15th Cloud Control
Workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; shortly before the pandemic
happened, causing the series to pause briefly. This was the reboot, and as
before, it was a great deal of fun: good company, good food, beautiful location.
If you get the chance to go, take it if you can!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop is a really nice mix of keynote presentations – not too many and
not too long at 20 minutes (mostly) – and discussion sessions proposed
beforehand or on site by participants. I gave one of the keynotes, talking about
the challenges posed and opportunities offered by edge computing. Can share
slides on request, or when I decide on a good way to publish them!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also enjoyed many good discussions and conversations, topped off with a great
BBQ, but two topics stand out. First, a great discussion session organised by
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;anakli.inf.ethz.ch&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Prof. Ana Klimović&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; about serverless computing
which immediately triggered some thoughts about possible followup publications
from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edgeless-project.eu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EDGELESS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and collaboration possibilities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, several conversations on a topic I know little about, low-earth orbit
(LEO) satellite networking, and what could be done with it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, my thought was whether a LEO constellation plus a little
edge compute could provide a difficult-to-disrupt out-of-band monitoring network
for critical infrastructure like datacenters and power grids: although data
bandwidth is limited and a bit complicated due to the constraints on ground
stations, they have pretty decent cameras, so why not use those to capture and
locally process images of the roofs of large rectangular buildings like
datacenters and the like which could continually display various status data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such status information would only need to be locally generated, so it would
take fairly substantial physical disruption of the facility (also presumably
noticeable by camera) to prevent that working. Alternatively, the constellation
(perhaps shared across multiple facilities in different jurisdictions) would
need to be substantially disrupted to prevent it being able to monitor targets.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a fun discussion anyway, combining a network technology I knew little
about with possibly interesting applications of edge computing to resiliency.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Postcript: in case you’re curious, the title is a passing reference to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Star_Trekkin%27&quot;&gt;Star
Trekkin’&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a fine popular music
single from my youth. Which has a much longer back-story on Wikipedia than I had
anticipated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Fame and Fortune!</title>
        <published>2015-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2015-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/bigtechday-mirage/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/bigtechday-mirage/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/bigtechday-mirage/">&lt;p&gt;After a slew of HDI related items, a quick &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;openmirage.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MirageOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; note. I was invited to
give a presentation on MirageOS at the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tngtech.com&#x2F;en.html&quot;&gt;TNG&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tngtech.com&#x2F;en&#x2F;big-techday.html&quot;&gt;Big TechDay 8&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; conference. This
was an interesting, and very broad based, event. It brought together about 500
people with about 25 speakers over one day, on topics from cognitive science to
AI to chess playing algorithms to obviating testing through proof reasoning.
And, of course, operating systems and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;openmirage.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MirageOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;! If you’re interested, the
slides used are available at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;decks.openmirage.org&#x2F;bigtechday8&quot;&gt;decks.openmirage.org&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in the usual
way, and if you really want to hear me droning on, TNG are making the video
(with synchronised slides)
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.techcast.com&#x2F;events&#x2F;bigtechday8&#x2F;salvator-1130&#x2F;?q=salvator-1130&quot;&gt;available&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As ever, comments welcome!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Actual HCI Papers!</title>
        <published>2015-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2015-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/ecscw-and-aarhus/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/ecscw-and-aarhus/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/ecscw-and-aarhus/">&lt;p&gt;I have to confess to being quite pleased to having a couple of
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hdiresearch.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;-related papers accepted recently (even if we
can’t even get proper reviews on the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;ssrn.com&#x2F;abstract=2508051&quot;&gt;original HDI paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; – recently judged
out-of-scope for the third time, even though the Special Issue in question
seemed bang on target!).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is a full paper to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ecscw2015.no&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ECSCW’15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; titled
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mor1.github.io&#x2F;publications&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;ecscw15-hdi.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Human Data Interaction: Historical Lessons from Social Studies and CSCW&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
A collaboration with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.andy-crabtree.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dr Andy Crabtree&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, it
examines particularly the role of &lt;em&gt;interaction&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in HDI and explores how past
technical approaches, such as
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mor1.github.io&#x2F;publications&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;comsnets11-dataware.pdf&quot;&gt;Dataware&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, to
the challenges posed by HDI haven’t fully considered the inherently social
nature of data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is a short paper to the decennial – seriously: every ten years! –
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;aarhus2015.org&quot;&gt;Aarhus 2015&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; conference titled
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mor1.github.io&#x2F;publications&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;aarhus15-databox.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Personal Data: Thinking Inside the Box&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
This sets out a vision for an embodiment of a &lt;em&gt;Databox&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: a physical device
supported by online services that empowers us to take back control of our online
lives. Building a Databox, using &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mirage.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MirageOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, is hopefully
going to be a key activity for me in the coming months…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Taking it to the People People</title>
        <published>2015-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2015-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/hdi-seminar/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/hdi-seminar/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/hdi-seminar/">&lt;p&gt;Looks like I get a chance to run my mouth off again :) Upcoming
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hdiresearch.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.crassh.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;events&#x2F;26198&quot;&gt;research
seminar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, organised by &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.bigdata.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cambridge Big
Data&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x2F;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.digitalhumanities.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Digital
Humanities&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. In short, details are:
&lt;strong&gt;20th April 2015, 14:00–16:00&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;S1, Alison Richard Building, West Road,
Cambridge&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. If you’d like to attend, please do register at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.eventbrite.co.uk&#x2F;e&#x2F;human-data-interaction-cambridge-big-datadigital-humanities-seminar-tickets-16337148852&quot;&gt;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.eventbrite.co.uk&#x2F;e&#x2F;human-data-interaction-cambridge-big-datadigital-humanities-seminar-tickets-16337148852&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just because pixels are, in some loose sense, nearly free, here’s the
abstract from the seminar link above:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increasing generation and collection of personal data has created a
complex ecosystem, often collaborative but sometimes combative, around
companies and individuals engaging in the use of these data. We propose that
the interactions between these agents warrant a new topic of study: Human-Data
Interaction (HDI), that sits at the intersection of various disciplines,
including computer science, statistics, sociology, psychology and behavioural
economics._&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this brief presentation I will pose some of the challenges that HDI raises,
organised into three core themes of legibility, agency and negotiability. I
will also outline some of the technical work we are currently undertaking that
attempts to address some of the underlying platform problems. My hope is to
elicit discussion of both the HDI framework and the technical solutions we are
pursuing, as well as to engage in a broader conversation about the ways we
should approach the personal data ecosystem with other interested parties._&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>I Think Someone Else Is Also Following Me...</title>
        <published>2015-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2015-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/being-followed-postscript/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/being-followed-postscript/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/being-followed-postscript/">&lt;p&gt;Turns out others were listening too – notably the USA’s &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.darpa.mil&#x2F;&quot;&gt;DARPA&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The recent
announcement of the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.darpa.mil&#x2F;NewsEvents&#x2F;Releases&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;11.aspx&quot;&gt;Brandeis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; programme makes explicit reference to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;ssrn.com&#x2F;abstract=2508051&quot;&gt;HDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hdiresearch.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;our website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. This has been picked up by &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;gcn.com&#x2F;articles&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;12&#x2F;darpa-brandeis.aspx&quot;&gt;GCN&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usatoday.com&#x2F;story&#x2F;nation&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;16&#x2F;data-privacy-darpa-brandeis&#x2F;70222556&#x2F;&quot;&gt;USAToday&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.nbcnews.com&#x2F;tech&#x2F;security&#x2F;darpa-unexpectedly-announces-program-improve-online-piracy-n322601&quot;&gt;NBCNews&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.engadget.com&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;12&#x2F;darpa-is-trying-to-reinvent-online-privacy&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Engadget&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; among others. With $60M potentially on the table, I
hope that there’ll be many more who get interested in pushing HDI forwards now
:)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>I Think Someone&#x27;s Following Me...</title>
        <published>2015-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2015-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/someones-following-me/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/someones-following-me/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/someones-following-me/">&lt;p&gt;It’s always&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; nice when someone notices what you’re doing, and I was
pleasantly surprised recently to find that someone had indeed been watching.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-2-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, it appears that someone at MIT Technology Review has noticed the
work of me and some of my pals: our work on &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;2015&#x2F;01&#x2F;05&#x2F;169715&#x2F;the-emerging-science-of-human-data-interaction&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HDI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and a recent sketch of some
follow-on work we’re pursuing around building a personal &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;2015&#x2F;01&#x2F;26&#x2F;169495&#x2F;how-a-box-could-solve-the-personal-data-conundrum&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Databox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Independently of that, the latter also happened to get picked up by
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theguardian.com&#x2F;profile&#x2F;johnnaughton&quot;&gt;John Naughton&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theguardian.com&#x2F;technology&#x2F;2015&#x2F;feb&#x2F;01&#x2F;control-personal-data-databox-end-user-agreement&quot;&gt;Guardian&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which ended up with a pretty
active comments thread, including one from Richard Stallman himself…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guess we’d better get on and deliver it now then :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, usually. Unless you’re doing something embarrassing like, e.g.,
dancing. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though in fact, given the pattern involved, I suspect it may be my
colleague, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk&#x2F;~hamed&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dr Hamed Haddadi&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; who’s
actually being followed. To whit, the fact that they also picked up on &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;2014&#x2F;09&#x2F;12&#x2F;171400&#x2F;the-murky-world-of-third-party-web-tracking&#x2F;&quot;&gt;a
study&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
of third-party web-tracking from last year. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-2-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Talks, Old and New</title>
        <published>2015-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2015-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/talks-old-and-new/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/talks-old-and-new/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/talks-old-and-new/">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to an invitation from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;um&#x2F;people&#x2F;hiballan&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Hitesh&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I recently got the chance to revisit my
old stomping ground at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;labs&#x2F;cambridge&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Microsoft Research Cambridge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Well, I say “old”
– in the intervening 7 years, they’ve moved to a rather splendid new building
at the other end of Cambridge, just next to the station. (And improved the
coffee too, not that it wasn’t pretty good to start with!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this was a pleasant chance to catch up with some old colleagues, meet
some new ones, and even speak to my most recently graduated Ph.D. student,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;people&#x2F;a-ewluge&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dr Ewa Luger&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; – and who’d’ve thought that I’d ever end up supervising
someone coming from the discipline of Political Science too!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ostensible reason was to talk about the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;homenetworks.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Homework&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; project – a talk I’ve
given a &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=AdtVSrazVaQ&quot;&gt;few times now&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; – and to lead from that into discussing some
of my current agenda, around &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hdiresearch.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Human-Data Interaction&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mort.io&#x2F;research&#x2F;&quot;&gt;User-Centred Systems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It seemed to go pretty well – a few
questions, and some lively discussion over lunch followed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happily, the fine folk at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;en-us&#x2F;labs&#x2F;cambridge&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MSRC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; recorded it and have made it available, so if
you’re really interested, you can take a look – direct your browser of choice to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;apps&#x2F;video&#x2F;default.aspx?id=238157&quot;&gt;Interacting with Infrastructure: Home Networking and Beyond&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say, when I checked that link in the course of writing this, one thing
that did come as something of a surprise was to notice that a talk I didn’t
remember giving – it was 8 years ago to be fair! – is also available. So if
you’ve a burning desire to find out about
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;research.microsoft.com&#x2F;apps&#x2F;video&#x2F;default.aspx?id=104278&quot;&gt;Measuring and Monitoring Microsoft’s Enterprise Network&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
it turns out you can do that too. The past haunts us they say. In my case, it
seems that the haunting has happened already, and turned my hair mostly white in
the process… :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
