<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>mort’s mythopœia - travel</title>
      <link>https://mort.io</link>
      <description>with apologies</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://mort.io/tags/travel/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Retreat from TUM</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/tum-retreat/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/tum-retreat/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/tum-retreat/">&lt;p&gt;Ok, ok, I exaggerate – it’s not really that far. But any time I have to set the
alarm for 02.30, it feels like it’s a long long way away!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;research-group&#x2F;&quot;&gt;TU Munchen&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; host an &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;events&#x2F;mir3&#x2F;&quot;&gt;annual
retreat&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and thanks to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;research-group&#x2F;joerg-ott&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Prof. Joerg
Ott&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; I was invited this
year for the first time. It’s held in TUM’s &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.raitenhaslach.tum.de&#x2F;en&#x2F;raitenhaslach&#x2F;home&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Retreat Centre at
Raitenhaslach&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
originally a Cistercian monastery which is a lovely location except that it’s a
bus ride from the hotel used and a bus and three trains from the nearest airport
– which is, mildly confusingly,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.salzburg-airport.com&#x2F;en&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Salzburg&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; not
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.munich-airport.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Munich&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The latter point made me assume that
there would be good directions via public transport from Salzburg, but that
turned out not to be the case. And as Google Maps is, at best, patchy in terms
of public transport coverage in this part of the world – it doesn’t know about
all the buses at least – I thought it might be useful to record the process of
getting there from Cambridge.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;events&#x2F;mir3&#x2F;mir3-2024-10&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;photo.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of the presenter in next to a slide in an ornately
    decorated room&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, to fly to Salzburg or Munich? In the end I picked Salzburg as it was
closer to the retreat centre itself and meant I didn’t need to fly via Heathrow
or Gatwick. As I had to be in Cambridge the night before for family reasons,
picking a closer airport for my very early flight seemed sensible. Unfortunately
this means flying Wizzair UK from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.london-luton.co.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;London Luton
Airport&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which after just twice flying from
there remains my least favourite UK airport. Given the flight departed at 05.55,
a £77.50 taxi from Cambridge was the only option.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per Panther’s recommmendation I allowed 70 minutes for the journey, and on my
own recommendation I aimed to arrive ~1.5h before the flight resulting in a taxi
booking for 03.15. Happily when I get in the taxi the driver said it would be
around 45-50 minutes, which was nice. Less happily when I checked in the day
before – using a laptop as neither Safari nor Firefox on iOS was able to
display the boarding pass – I got an automatic email from Wizzair telling me
that I needed to arrive at the airport by 02.15 as the airport was upgrading
their “central search facilities”. After trying to call the airport half a dozen
times but getting trapped in the IVR menus at the inevitable “read the FAQ on
the website” end state, I gave up trying to check if that really was necessary
and decided to risk my original timings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did however spot one useful thing: “prebooked security check”. This appears to
be the ability to book, at 15 minute granularity, a security check during peak
hours (03.00-04.30). Given my estimated arrival time of 04.15, that seemed
perfect.
 &lt;img src=&quot;road.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of a road being worked&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;

As it was also &lt;strong&gt;completely free&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; requiring nothing more than my
flight number and an email address (not even the one associated with my ticket),
I booked it resulting in an email with a QR code to show to security. This
worked perfectly when I arrived at the airport: show the person on security the
QR code on the phone screen, and they simply jump you past the security queue to
the front. Did I mention this was completely free? Seems a strange system to me
but hey, I’ll take it!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, the public transport worked though there was a short walk at the end
that was longer than I expected – rebuilding a road meant I could get through
but the bus couldn’t! And then the retreat happened – but you can &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ce.cit.tum.de&#x2F;cm&#x2F;events&#x2F;mir3&#x2F;mir3-2024-10&#x2F;&quot;&gt;read about
that elsewhere&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Rat Racing Jetlag</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/jetlag-fasting/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/jetlag-fasting/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/jetlag-fasting/">&lt;p&gt;As I’ve found myself repeating the same information several times recently, and
have to dig out the links in question every time, I figured it’d be useful to
write this down once so I can point at it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jetlag is a first-world problem but can be an annoying one– in recent years
I’ve found I have a particular problem getting up in the morning when flying
east. So, one day, bored in an airport in the US and with only the entire
Internet to hand, I thought I’d look around for an explanation at least.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up coming across reports of some physiological research – in rats of
course – that suggested a way to avoid jetlag. I’ve since tried it over a dozen
times, and found it to work in all cases. At this point I no longer care if it’s
placebo affect or a genuine explanation or something else :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TL;DR is: fast for &amp;gt;16 hours before your time of arrival, then eat as
appropriate. Definitely &amp;gt;16 hours though – the occasions I’ve not quite managed
it (at least once I miscounted and managed only about 14 hours) it didn’t seem
to work as effectively.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I interpret the information in the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;dx.doi.org&#x2F;10.1126&#x2F;science.1153277&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, found via
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;news.bbc.co.uk&#x2F;2&#x2F;hi&#x2F;health&#x2F;7414437.stm&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;news.harvard.edu&#x2F;gazette&#x2F;story&#x2F;2008&#x2F;05&#x2F;study-identifies-food-related-clock-in-the-brain&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Harvard&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
reports, through my “I can barely do computer science and certainly not biology”
brain, mammals have two body clocks, one driven by daylight and one by
metabolism. The daylight can’t be shifted quickly, but the metabolic one can be
made to float by fasting. The metabolic also being a lower level clock means
that, when you resync it by consuming calories, it syncs back to whatever light
conditions are current.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I say, this isn’t my area of expertise – but it seems to work anyway.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, because a surprisingly large (or perhaps not) number of people also ask–
as far as I know and have experienced, fasting means &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; calories,
&lt;strong&gt;including alcohol&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, even it it’s free… :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
