<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>mort’s mythopœia - teaching</title>
    <subtitle>with apologies</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://mort.io/tags/teaching/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2024-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mort.io/tags/teaching/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part II Projects</title>
        <published>2024-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/part-ii-projects/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/part-ii-projects/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/part-ii-projects/">&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate final-year (“Part II”) project supervision goes in fits and
starts. After a couple of years of having almost no interest, this year I’ve had
several enquiries and it seems I might end supervising 3–4 projects. So
herewith a record of the things I’ve found myself repeating!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-structure&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#project-structure&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: project-structure&quot;&gt;Project structure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key thing for the structure of the project is to make sure that there is a
core piece that is (essentially) guaranteed to be deliverable. This is the piece
that you know you can do, and once done and written up, you know you can get an
adequate (if not great) mark. Ensuring this takes the risk out of the project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of this core piece, it’s then usually sensible to build “a few” (2? 3?
4?) extensions which will make the project spicy if done well. You may wish to
phrase these extensions as “for example, extensions might include…” or words
to that effect, to give some wiggle room in the final dissertation. Getting
these done successfully is what should put you in line for a very good mark
rather than a simply adequate mark.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-framing&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#project-framing&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: project-framing&quot;&gt;Project framing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also very helpful, particularly if you are aiming for a high mark, to try
to frame the project in terms of &lt;strong&gt;a research question you will answer&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; rather
than &lt;strong&gt;an artefact you will build&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Often in systems the appropriate way to
answer the research questions we pose will be to build an artefact – but by
framing it in terms of the question you seek to answer, it makes it easier to
write the dissertation as a piece of research rather than a &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Small_matter_of_programming&quot;&gt;small matter of
programming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Empirically, this seems to have an outsize effect on the chances of the
examiners thinking the project difficult and marking accordingly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can also be useful to try to be explicit about where your project requires
you to go beyond the CST taught material, particularly from Part IA&#x2F;IB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-proposal&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#project-proposal&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: project-proposal&quot;&gt;Project proposal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my mind there are two critical pieces of the proposal around which everything
else sits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the &lt;strong&gt;evaluation plan&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: if you can write this well, then you understand
what you’re going to build, and what it means to have done it well (or badly).
Writing the evaluation plan therefore usually means you have, for the most part,
got the rest of the project figured out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the &lt;strong&gt;workplan&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: this divides time until submission into two week
(never larger, sometimes smaller) chunks, each of which has attached a &lt;em&gt;calendar
date&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (so there’s no confusion over weeks in term or suchlike) and a
&lt;em&gt;milestone&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x2F;&lt;em&gt;deliverable&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (so that we can immediately tell whether you’ve
completed, or at least are making progress against, that chunk of work in our
weekly meeting). Don’t forget to take account of any relevant module assessment
deadlines in your plan!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it’s a plan not a contract! You don’t lose marks because you deviate
from the plan– but if you can’t tell whether you’re ahead or behind, you might
well find yourself in a sticky position at the end of Lent term or start of
Easter term when you find you’ve got module assessments to complete, revision to
start, two weeks to go until dissertation submission and still four weeks of
work to do on your project…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;supervision-process&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#supervision-process&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: supervision-process&quot;&gt;Supervision process&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I normally supervise projects by scheduling weekly half-hour meetings with each
student. Longer meetings can be arranged on an ad hoc basis as required. The key
purpose of the meeting is to check progress against the workplan, and to make
sure that any difficulties and roadblocks are aired and dealt with (whether in
the meeting or by scheduling a longer discussion).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example of a reasonable target timeline, consider trying to get
implementation completed by the end of Christmas vacation, evaluation completed
by the division of Lent Term, and the dissertation completed by the end of Lent
Term. That then gives you flexibility as to whether you do more project work,
extensions etc., or focus on exam revision, or whatever.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully that’s helpful. At the very least, I can now point potential project
students at it, so it’s helpful for me :) Some of the above may also be relevant
writing research proposals (Part III &#x2F; MPhil projects, even Ph.D.s) but that’s a
topic for another day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
