<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>mort’s mythopœia - policy</title>
    <subtitle>with apologies</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://mort.io/tags/policy/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2026-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mort.io/tags/policy/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Some Remarks on the Risks of Lawful Access</title>
        <published>2026-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Richard Mortier
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mort.io/blog/cosi-lawful-access/"/>
        <id>https://mort.io/blog/cosi-lawful-access/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/cosi-lawful-access/">&lt;p&gt;Last summer I was invited to participate in an informal meeting of the EU
Standing Committee on Operational Cooperation on Internal Security (COSI). The
session I was asked to join concerned end-to-end encryption (“E2EE”). I was
asked to “…set the scene for the discussion laying out in layman’s terms the
technical possibilities of access to data and the technical consequences of it”,
before being followed by the two other organizations presenting.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-chatham-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-chatham&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I present below the remarks I made. Unusually for me, I actually wrote down all
the words I intended to say in advance rather than using slides and winging it
in the usual way. The context and topic felt like it would be worth avoiding
slips of the tongue in this case. I gave it pretty much as written—even when I
try, I can’t help a small amount of ad libbing! But I did not deviate
significantly from this text.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having sought feedback from others on this, I would like to add a couple of
remarks as a preface.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the “Police Behaving Badly” paper puts the percentage of cybercrime
convictions involving police at 56% in the first half of 2024, and details how
police have had encrypted communication data but had it leaked by a corrupt
intelligence analyst advising her drug dealer friend that it was compromised.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, although I did try to be clear, I could have been more explicit that a
significant challenge in this space is the inevitability of software bugs.
(Approximately) All software contains bugs and it is almost certain that any
exceptional access system, due to the unavoidable complexity of such systems,
will contain bugs and so will not work as intended. The position I am trying to
take is that, while that is insufficient reason to reject every such proposal,
it is important to be realistic about the risks so that the costs and benefits
can be weighed rationally.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#who-am-i&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who am I?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I should introduce myself. I am Richard Mortier, more commonly known as
Mort. I am a professor in the Department of Computer Science &amp;amp; Technology at
Cambridge University, UK, and Fellow of Christ’s College, Cambridge. I
previously spent 6 years as a researcher with Microsoft Research Cambridge,
and 6 months with Sprint Advanced Technology Labs, California, and I have
founded three startups. I am currently also a member of the UK’s Investigatory
Powers’ Commissioner’s Office Technology Advisory Panel.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primary expertise is in computer systems and networking, and human-computer
interaction. I thus speak on this topic as a computer scientist with general
expertise in computer systems rather than as a specialist in encryption or
messaging systems. I make these remarks in a personal capacity, representing
no-one’s views but my own.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-debate&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#this-debate&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: this-debate&quot;&gt;This debate&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been asked to speak to you today about &lt;strong&gt;lawful&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;exceptional
access&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. I will stay above the nitty-gritty technical details of encryption,
communications protocols and so on, while still staying sufficiently grounded
in technology that this is not a purely abstract, philosophical debate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My impression of this debate is that it can often descend into an unhelpful
back and forth between two extreme positions that I might simplistically
characterize as “We must provide lawful access—think of the children!” and
“We cannot provide lawful access—privacy is a fundamental right!”. “We
must!” “We can’t!” and so on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-position&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#my-position&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: my-position&quot;&gt;My position&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish to re-frame this debate to place those positions at the two extremes of
what is actually a spectrum of possibilities ranging from one where we have
mechanisms to provide perfectly secure, invisible communication among group
members where groups can form and dissolve on an ad hoc basis, to one where no
communication is possible without authorized bodies having full access to all
communication content and metadata.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither extreme is sensible or achievable in my view—but intermediate
positions might be. The basis for a society to decide where it wants to be on
that spectrum requires articulation and evaluation of the risks involved. I
observe, as a computer scientist, that building any large-scale
network-connected secure system is complex, and all complexity has costs and
introduces risks. Typically, the more complex, the more cost and the more
risk. Implementation of lawful access mechanisms is inevitably complex as they
are powerful and must be secured against external and internal bad actors.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This needs to be acknowledged in the discussion. These are not trivial
mechanisms and may even involve research activity in order to articulate the
design space and understand the trade-offs involved. Justification for these
mechanisms thus needs to be stronger than “we once had this ability, so we are
worried about losing it”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;relevant-terms&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#relevant-terms&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: relevant-terms&quot;&gt;Relevant terms&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will define some relevant terms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encryption&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; refers to the transformation of &lt;em&gt;plain text&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; information into a
&lt;em&gt;cipher text&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; such that only the authorized parties can decrypt the cipher
text, transforming it back into the plain text. Such transformations are
usually described in mathematical terms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;encryption scheme&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is a scheme for exchanging secret data over an
insecure channel using encryption. As they are based on mathematical
operations, it is generally possible to give guarantees about how
computationally difficult it is to, for example, work out the plain text that
produced a given cipher text—that is, to break the encryption scheme.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many such schemes with a range of trade-offs between complexity,
computational cost, and how difficult they make it for an unauthorized party
to decrypt a cipher text. All rely at some level on the creation and
consumption of secret &lt;strong&gt;key material&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to perform transformations between
plain text and cipher text.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, an encryption scheme has to be reduced to an implementation,
usually in software. It takes considerable effort to ensure that a given
implementation correctly implements the encryption scheme, and even more
effort to ensure that it does not leak information about the plain text
message or the secret key material during encryption or (attempted)
decryption.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secure messaging systems&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; are Internet-connected services that provide for
exchange of messages between two or more individual devices. Older systems
provide message exchange by having devices send messages to central servers
that then replicate those messages, transmitting them to other devices
participating in the conversation. This requires those central servers to have
access to the secret key material so that they can decrypt messages to work
out where to send them on to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End-to-end encryption&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; refers to those encryption systems where this is not
the case: the central servers that assist in replication of messages to the
intended recipients do not have access to the secret key material and so
cannot decrypt the encrypted messages. Only the participating devices can do
that. End-to-end encryption is increasingly common in consumer-grade messaging
applications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;lawful&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (or &lt;strong&gt;exceptional&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;) &lt;strong&gt;access&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in this context refers to
technical mechanisms provided to enable authorized bodies such as law
enforcement and intelligence services to access communications systems on
production of suitable authorization. In the UK, for example, this would
entail the relevant body seeking a suitable warrant under the Investigatory
Powers Act (2016) as amended. Lawful access mechanisms have historically been
provided in many communication systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-problem&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End-to-end encryption does make provision of lawful access more difficult: the
secret key material is in principle never held by the service provider and so
they cannot simply grant access to messages. Mechanisms would need to be added
to enable such access. But as soon as any mechanism exists for a third party
to gain access to decrypted messages, bad actors will also seek to exploit it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such mechanisms are powerful, as with any additional feature they add
complexity and increase the likelihood of creating vulnerabilities that can be
attacked. And so the argument goes that we &lt;strong&gt;cannot&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; provide lawful access
mechanisms because it would be irresponsible to do so, weakening protections
that law-abiding members of society rely upon for so many different purposes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, so the counter-argument continues, lawful access is necessary to protect
the public including the vulnerable and children. Bad actors make use of
secure messaging services to exchange illegal material, to plan and execute
serious crimes, to commit terrorism and so forth. So mechanisms for lawful
access &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; be provided otherwise it is impossible for law enforcement to
carry out their duties to enforce the law and protect society. And so the
argument continues that we must provide mechanisms for lawful access.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t. We must. We can’t. We must. Both positions are extreme points in a
spectrum of risk. What I believe we can and must do is take a risk-based
approach to this challenge: articulate the risks and, if we decide they are
worth taking, develop mechanisms to mitigate them. Lawful access can be done
and has been done—but should it be done, and how?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;two-principles&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#two-principles&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: two-principles&quot;&gt;Two principles&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what are the principles to consider, what risks do such mechanisms create,
and how might we consider them?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first principle is that any lawful access mechanism is, by definition,
powerful. It allows an authorized party to access information that people wish
to keep secret. It is not therefore something that is easy to design,
implement, test, maintain and operate: considerable care will be required, and
potentially considerable expense incurred.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is that any such mechanism can and will be abused. Bad actors will
seek to exploit it to gain access to information, and may well succeed from
time to time. Those unauthorized accesses will come from external bad actors
but also internal bad actors. As well as the maintenance costs this creates,
it also suggests that accountability and transparency are critical.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;~ah793&#x2F;cccd.html&quot;&gt;Cambridge Computer Crime
Database&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a database of
cybercrime events of many kinds where the offender or alleged offender has
been arrested, charged and&#x2F;or prosecuted in the UK, dating from 1 January
2010. In the last 6 months of 2023, nearly half of the cases involved police
as offenders. I am not saying that these directly involve lawful access or
similar mechanisms, or that such incidents are commonplace—but it is
undeniable that they do occur, and that lawful access mechanisms could create
another route by which they can be carried out. Bad actors will also be
present in the service providers. Strong powers require strong oversight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate cannot continue under the assumptions that this is a
straightforward technology to build and protect against unauthorized use, and
that authorized users will always use it lawfully.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;thinking-about-risk-necessity-proportionality&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#thinking-about-risk-necessity-proportionality&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: thinking-about-risk-necessity-proportionality&quot;&gt;Thinking about risk: necessity &amp;amp; proportionality&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is useful to think about the risks from a perspective of necessity
and proportionality.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;strong&gt;necessity&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: what is it that lawful access enables, and why?
Mechanisms could be built to enable a range of types of lawful access. For
example, access to the content of all messages; access to the content of all
messages involving certain keywords or with attached images that trigger some
flag; access to the content of all messages involving certain participants;
access to the content of selected messages; or access to metadata about
messages such as participant identifiers, message timestamps, locations of
transmission and reception, whether for all messages, all messages involving
certain parties, or specific messages. To determine what access is appropriate
requires articulating the purpose: to what use will the information be put? By
whom? And are there really no existing mechanisms by which the desired outcome
can be achieved?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;strong&gt;proportionality&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: what are the effects of exercising lawful access,
and how are the harms to be balanced against the benefits? All the mechanisms
listed above create risks when abused—but some create more risks than
others. Creating an ability, however well protected, to read any and all
messages between any communicating parties clearly creates enormous potential
for privacy infringement and crime. Creating an ability simply to know which
accounts communicated and when also creates risks but perhaps lesser ones in
most cases.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These perspectives need to be tested and debated before suitable mechanisms
can be designed, implemented, and exercised. Oversight mechanisms—perhaps
including by non-governmental organizations—need to be part of the design.
The intended benefits need to be articulated. Usage and impact need to be
tracked. Scope creep and the ability to silently expand the reach of such a
capability to enable mass surveillance needs to be guarded against. Comparison
needs to be made against alternative current approaches. For example, a
warrant can be obtained to hack a target’s phone giving access to all content
on that device, not just their messages; is that more or less intrusive than
providing a mechanism that enables selected messages or communications’
metadata to be obtained on presentation of a suitable warrant, but which
simply cannot be used to reveal any other content?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world where, as I understand it, policing resources are constantly being
stretched, how will law enforcement ensure it has the capacity to use
effectively information gained via such lawful access mechanisms? The risks
created by these mechanisms, once deployed, are always present even when they
are not being legally exercised: creating the mechanisms and then not
effectively using them considerably reduces any proportionality argument. If
the resource to sift existing data is already stretched, how will putting more
hay on the haystack help in finding the needles?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the success of operations against systems such as
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;EncroChat&quot;&gt;Encrochat&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.bbc.co.uk&#x2F;news&#x2F;articles&#x2F;clyljpygxgjo&quot;&gt;Ghost&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; raises the question:
is it enough to concentrate on those systems that target criminal use? How
much extra will be gained by creating lawful access mechanisms in
consumer-grade systems? I am not saying nothing will be gained—but the
expected benefits need to be quantified for the case to be made.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the call for lawful access mechanisms based on specific, recorded instances
where they would have made a material difference to society? Or is it based
primarily on fear of a future where once useful mechanisms cease to be
available? “Once we could but now we cannot” is not a very strong argument for
necessity and proportionality given the way that technology has constantly
evolved over decades and centuries.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Communications_Assistance_for_Law_Enforcement_Act&quot;&gt;Communications Assistance for Law Enforcement Act (CALEA)
1994&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
enforced US communications providers to implement wire-tapping capabilities.
It also mandated that those providers secure their networks. Unfortunately, it
seems that the implementation of &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.schneier.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;archives&#x2F;2025&#x2F;04&#x2F;arguing-against-calea.html&quot;&gt;that capability created a risk that was
exploited&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
by a group dubbed &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;techcrunch.com&#x2F;2024&#x2F;10&#x2F;07&#x2F;the-30-year-old-internet-backdoor-law-that-came-back-to-bite&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Salt
Typhoon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
to allow capture of sensitive call metadata in Washington D.C. Experts have
been reported as saying that such an attack was “inevitable”. How can such
risks, in terms of both likelihood and impact, be quantified and weighed in
the balance?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-solutions&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#non-solutions&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: non-solutions&quot;&gt;Non-solutions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth at this point dismissing some ways that have in the past been
proposed for lawful access but which have very significant problems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, deliberately weakening encryption schemes. This simply does not work in
practice: bad actors will use more secure schemes anyway, and will seek to
exploit law-abiding services that use the weakened schemes, putting
law-abiding users at risk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, forms of key escrow. This is where the secret key material is placed
under the control of some trusted party, and can be accessed on presentation
of a suitably authorized request. Unfortunately, this allows anyone who can
produce, whether or not legitimately, such a request to access &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;
communications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, ghost users. This is where providers add law enforcement operatives to
chats without triggering notifications or otherwise informing chat
participants that a new member has been added. While in some ways technically
attractive, as described such a mechanism provides no means for accountability
and oversight: what record is made, and how is it inspected, that such an
action was carried out by the service provider, for what purpose, at what
time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-possible-solution&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#a-possible-solution&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: a-possible-solution&quot;&gt;A possible solution&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will close by sketching &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;martin.kleppmann.com&#x2F;2021&#x2F;07&#x2F;16&#x2F;cryptographic-backdoors-hotpets.html&quot;&gt;a proposal from a colleague, Dr Martin
Kleppmann&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
for a lawful access mechanism that seeks to balance benefits and harms,
published at the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;petsymposium.org&#x2F;2021&#x2F;hotpets.php&quot;&gt;HotPETS (Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium) Workshop
in 2021&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It seeks to ensure that
undetectable mass surveillance cannot be carried out, and that oversight can
be exercised in relevant jurisdictions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, it provides a public &lt;em&gt;transparency log&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; into which all accepted
lawful access requests are written with a few publicly readable fields
indicating the requesting body, the warrant jurisdiction, its basis and
validity period, plus some cryptographic commitment as to the target for the
warrant. Thus, anyone can see how many warrants are being issued, why, and
when &lt;em&gt;without the targets being revealed&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service’s client application then checks the log and if it finds a valid
entry for the device it is running on, it uploads the requested data for the
indicated period to the specified LEA. This is similar to the message backup
procedure already provided for by many secure messaging applications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, a trusted oversight body in the jurisdiction can cross-check
log entries against issued warrants, and require the service provider to
reveal the targets of those warrants so that proportionality can be justified
by reference to the seriousness of the crime of which they are accused.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provides targeted upload of data, reducing the ease with which bad actors
can use it to acquire data themselves. It enables interested parties, perhaps
including civil society organizations, to monitor general use of the mechanism
so that moves towards mass surveillance can be detected. It enables trusted
oversight bodies to exercise powers to inspect and ensure that necessity and
proportionality requirements are being met.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a fully worked up proposal, and it does not thoroughly address
every possible challenge. To produce such a proposal would require, as well as
some of the discussion and debate referred to above, more technical details
about how the communications services that would be subject to such mechanisms
are architected and operated. But it hopefully serves as an example of an
approach that sits on the spectrum somewhere between “We can’t” and “We must”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#conclusions&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary then,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe that it is in principle possible to design, implement and deploy
lawful access mechanisms, even in end-to-end encrypted systems.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But doing so requires careful justification as to necessity and
proportionality: just because such mechanisms could be built and would be
useful does not automatically mean that they should be built.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Such justification must include realistic consideration of the risks even
just the existence of such mechanisms would introduce, as well as
mechanisms to mitigate those risks.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To maintain public trust in secure communications means that such strong
powers must be designed and implemented so as to enable strong oversight
by trusted bodies, likely including non-governmental bodies.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#references&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: references&quot;&gt;References&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.lawfaremedia.org&#x2F;article&#x2F;principles-more-informed-exceptional-access-debate&quot;&gt;Principles for a More Informed Exceptional Access Debate&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”,
Ian Levy &amp;amp; Crispin Robinson. 29 November 2018.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;~ah793&#x2F;papers&#x2F;2019inside_out.pdf&quot;&gt;Inside out: Characterising cybercrimes committed inside and outside the
workplace&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”.
Alice Hutchings and Ben Collier, Cambridge University. IEEE European
Symposium on Security and Privacy Workshops (EuroS&amp;amp;PW) 2019, pp. 481– 490.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gov.uk&#x2F;government&#x2F;publications&#x2F;open-letter-to-mark-zuckerberg&#x2F;written-testimony-of-chloe-squires-director-national-security-home-office&quot;&gt;Judiciary Committee United States Senate hearing: Encryption and Lawful
Access: Evaluating Benefits and Risks to Public Safety and Privacy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”,
Chloe Squires, Director National Security, Home Office. 23 December 2019.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;securephones.io&#x2F;main.html&quot;&gt;Data Security on Mobile Devices: Current State of the Art, Open
Problems, and Proposed Solutions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”,
Maximilian Zinkus, Tushar M. Jois, Matthew Green, Johns Hopkins
University. 6 June 2021.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;martin.kleppmann.com&#x2F;papers&#x2F;backdoors-hotpets21.pdf&quot;&gt;Harm Reduction for Cryptographic
Backdoors&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”,
Martin Kleppmann, Cambridge University. 14th Workshop on Hot Topics in
Privacy Enhancing Technologies (HotPETs). 16 July 2021.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;home-affairs.ec.europa.eu&#x2F;networks&#x2F;high-level-group-hlg-access-data-effective-law-enforcement_en#recommendations&quot;&gt;Concluding report of the High-Level Group on access to data for
effective law enforcement&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”.
15 November 2024.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;~ah793&#x2F;papers&#x2F;2025police.pdf&quot;&gt;Police behaving
badly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;”. Alice
Hutchings, Cambridge University. IEEE Security and Privacy, 23(1),
pp.80-82. 4 February 2025.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-chatham&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A la the Chatham House Rule, we were asked not to reveal identities
of participants or the organizations they represented. I was there
in a private capacity, giving my own views as an academic computer
scientist. You might choose to guess who might be the sorts of
organization not in COSI with a stake in this debate; I couldn’t
possibly comment. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-chatham-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
