<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>mort’s mythopœia - phd</title>
      <link>https://mort.io</link>
      <description>with apologies</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://mort.io/tags/phd/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Rewarding influence</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/happy-day/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;2025.eurosys.org&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;EuroSys 2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; was co-located with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; this year. Other
commitments meant I (again) couldn’t stay for the whole conference, attending
primarily because &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;tdis-accepted&#x2F;&quot;&gt;two students had papers in the TDIS
workshop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&quot;stage.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fl pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of me in a yellow t-shirt receiving the award&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But happily I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; able to stay for the first day of the conference –
“happily” not only because it gave me a chance to catch up with some old friends
I hadn’t seen in a decade or more, but also because &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;2451116.2451167&quot;&gt;the Mirage unikernels
paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which appeared at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;asplos13.rice.edu&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2013&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; won one of two &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&#x2F;awards&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ASPLOS 2025 Influential Papers
awards&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is obviously very flattering – typically doing research is necessarily its
own reward because the work can seem fruitless much of the time. Even when a
paper gets written and submitted it will most likely be rejected – I think
EuroSys this year reported something like a 12% acceptance rate, so rejection is
&lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the most likely outcome. Finally, if the paper does finally get
accepted, it will most likely sink without trace – perhaps a brief flurry of
interest for a few months or so, the paper gets cited a few times, and then it
fades away. This seems inevitable in a reasonably fast moving field that is also
growing at pace – EuroSys had ~160 attendees in 2006, growing to ~330 in the 10
years to 2016, but hitting ~1100 this year; while submissions grew from ~200 in
2019 to 696 this year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&quot;official.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fr pd1&quot; alt=&quot;A photograph of the certificate&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to win an award recognising that others feel a paper actually had some
influence is rare, and makes me very happy :) At the same time, it reinforces a
couple of lessons that I really should’ve internalised by now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is that papers inevitably get better for thoughtful considered
feedback from experts a step or several away from the work – so drafts should
be produced in plenty of time and distributed to anyone who’s willing to take
the time for feedback. In the case of this paper the previous failed submission
to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usenix.org&#x2F;conference&#x2F;osdi12&quot;&gt;OSDI 2012&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; had, let’s say, reviews
of mixed quality. But one stood out, from Jon Howell (who signs his reviews so I
know it was him), who gave us a firm “reject” which (in retrospect) was actually
fairly well-deserved but in an incredibly constructive way. To paraphrase him
slightly, the work was interesting but the paper was crap – &lt;em&gt;and here’s how to
rewrite it so it makes sense&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. We basically did what he said, ASPLOS accepted
it, and the rest is now history. (Over a decade ago, good grief.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is that I simply cannot predict whether any research I’m doing is
actually going to turn out to have any value. The only other equivalent award
I’ve had was an &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;infocom2024.ieee-infocom.org&#x2F;awards&quot;&gt;INFOCOM 2024 Test of Time
award&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1109&#x2F;INFCOM.2012.6195845&quot;&gt;our 2012 paper on a
system called &lt;em&gt;Thinkair&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, about
mobile-code offload from devices to the cloud. That paper had received
considerably more than just one rejection prior to acceptance, and if I recall
my final contribution correctly, I recommended not submitting it to INFOCOM as I
didn’t think we’d done enough to address previous review comments.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shows what I know. But then, how boring would life be without a little
ignorance… :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Not one but two accepted papers and a Ph.D.</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/tdis-accepted/">&lt;p&gt;As I find myself once more on a train to parts unknown (to me at least), a brief
update :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parts unknown in question is Rotterdam, NL (so really quite well-known to
quite a lot of people, just not me) for &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;2025.eurosys.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;EURO&#x2F;SYS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (being held jointly with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.asplos-conference.org&#x2F;asplos2025&quot;&gt;ASPLOS
2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, although I can’t stay for
the whole thing unfortunately) and specifically the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tdis.gitlab.io&#x2F;tdis25&#x2F;&quot;&gt;3rd International Workshop
of Testing Distributed Internet of Things Systems
(TDIS)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Happily the programme committee decided to accept two papers from my
(ex-)students – which is nice :) The two in question are&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3719159.3721222&quot;&gt;Reckon-ing Kubernetes at the Edge using Emulated
Clusters&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; with Alessandro Sassi
(University of Cambridge &#x2F; Politecnico di Milano) and Christopher Jensen
(University of Cambridge &#x2F; Microsoft Research). This describes Alessandro’s
M.Sc. research project undertaken as a visitor with my group. He built on
Chris’ earlier work on &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3447851.3458739&quot;&gt;Reckon, an emulator setup for examining consensus
system behaviour&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Alessandor
extended this to use ContainerNet enabling it to emulate Kubernetes clusters
on a single node, and used this to examine Kubernetes performance in some
edge network scenarios. Source available on GitHub at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;AleSassi&#x2F;reckon-k8s&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;AleSassi&#x2F;reckon-k8s&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3719159.3721221&quot;&gt;LoRaLive: Efficient LoRaWAN Traffic
Generation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; with Vadim Safronov
(University of Oxford &#x2F; University of Cambridge). This reports a component of
Vadim’s Ph.D. work where he built a system to enable dense deployment LoRaWAN
trace-playback using a minimal number of nodes while respecting legal
constraints on duty cycles. Source available on GitHub at
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;LoRaLive&#x2F;LoRaLive&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;LoRaLive&#x2F;LoRaLive&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both nice tools that we hope might be of community interest!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ph.D. in question is Chris Jensen’s – happily he passed his viva on
Thursday just gone, titled “Separating conflict-recovery from failure-recovery
in distributed consensus”, examined by &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;timharris.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tim Harris&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;charap.co&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Aleksey Charapko&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Other recent passes include Al-Amjad
Tawfiq Isstaif, titled “Contention-resilient overcommitment for serverless
deployments” and Andrew Jeffery, titled “Modelling orchestration”. The race&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
is now on for the first to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cl.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;techreports&#x2F;&quot;&gt;tech
report&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not really a race. That would be weird. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>PhD viva, UK style</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/phd-viva/">&lt;p&gt;Having recently, happily, had several PhD students completing in short order,
I’ve been approaching external PhD examiners. Occasionally I find myself asking
someone who’s not done any &#x2F; many in the UK previously. As our system – as all
such systems! – is a bit different to those in other parts of the world, I’ve
written a few notes on a couple of occasions about what to expect. So I figured
I might as well publish them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is my impression &#x2F; understanding based on experience here in the
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cst.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Department of Computer Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cam.ac.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cambridge University&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; ca. 2025. Your Mileage May Vary
anywhen and anywhere else, including anywhere else in the UK – check local
regulations to be sure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of process, the system here is that candidates submit their complete
dissertation and then undergo a “viva voce” (oral examination). It would be
usual for the viva to take place within 2—3 months of submission. It’s better
(IMO, much better) if it can happen in person but we may still be able to
arrange to do it online in extremis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two examiners:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;internal examiner&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (typically connected to the Department) who ensures
the process is followed properly but may not be a deep expert in the specific
topic, and&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;external examiner&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (from outside the University) who is there as the
subject matter expert.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The viva consists of the two examiners asking the candidate questions about
their dissertation until they’re satisfied; typically this takes at least 2h and
can go longer, though more than 3.5—4h is unusual in my experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examiners are each expected to read the dissertation in detail before the
viva and each write a short (typically 1—2pp) independent report giving their
opinion, outlining any concerns they will have and the resulting
topics&#x2F;questions they will be exploring in the viva, and indicating what their a
priori judgement is in terms of recommendation (roughly: pass&#x2F;pass with
corrections&#x2F;revise &amp;amp; resubmit&#x2F;no Ph.D. but you can have a Masters&#x2F;fail).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examiners will then typically meet ~30min or so before the viva to discuss
their independent reports and decide on the approach to take in the viva. After
the viva they write a joint report (usually shorter than their independent
reports; perhaps 0.5pp) outlining what happened in the viva, as well as making a
final recommendation and providing (if appropriate) a list of corrections that
must be satisfied for the candidate to pass.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the University pays a (risibly small) honorarium to the external
examiner for doing the viva plus reasonable expenses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
