<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>mort’s mythopœia - interview</title>
      <link>https://mort.io</link>
      <description>with apologies</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://mort.io/tags/interview/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Google screening</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Richard Mortier</author>
          <link>https://mort.io/blog/google-screening/</link>
          <guid>https://mort.io/blog/google-screening/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mort.io/blog/google-screening/">&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, for reasons best known to themselves, a Google recruiter decided
to “reach out” on the basis of &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;mor1&#x2F;&quot;&gt;my GitHub profile&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to
see if I were interested in a role as a Site-Reliability Engineer or possibly a
Software Engineer. This entailed a short (~30min) telephone interview to answer
some questions. I made a note of those I recalled, in case anyone’s interested.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hawk-eyed and keen-minded among you may discern a certain amount of
ambiguity in answers to some of the questions – e.g., is the opposite of
&lt;code&gt;malloc()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;free()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or a garbage collector? are we assuming an Ethernet MAC
address? – which the recruiter did not seem to be happy to deal with. But so
long as my answer included a reasonable approximation to (presumably) the string
they had written down, all was well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the Big-O complexity of quicksort?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the search complexity for a red-black tree, a binary tree, a linked
list, a hashtable, and a B-tree?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s the opposite of &lt;code&gt;malloc()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the semantics of an ACL?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which of the following fields are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; part of the &lt;code&gt;passwd&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; file?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shell, comment, initial umask, login name, ui, home directory, gid,
preferred language&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What does the &lt;code&gt;fstat&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; syscall do?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s the default signal for &lt;code&gt;kill&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s in an inode?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you make a socket accept inbound connections?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many bytes in a MAC address?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the packets involved in a TCP connection setup?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many hosts are in a &#x2F;23 subnet?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s the DNS resource record type for an IPv6 address?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimate the value of 2&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I passed even though I could only remember the name, not the number,
of the default signal for &lt;code&gt;kill&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. It then got mildly amusing: the next stage is
apparently to “jump on a call” (sigh) with a recruiter and an engineer to work
through some coding problems. I explained that I generally refuse to engage in
whiteboard coding during interviews (it’s not a useful measure of anything
useful, and I don’t see why I should). They said oh but of course I could do it
on a call so it wouldn’t actually be a whiteboard. I said, yes I could but no I
wouldn’t and I thought they were rather missing my point. They said really,
it was very unusual for someone to refuse. I said, to be honest it makes little
sense anyway given they contacted me because of &lt;em&gt;all the code I’d written under
my GitHub account&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. They said oh well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then some time later – 6 months I think – a different recruiter “reached
out” to ask why the process had stalled and did I want to jump on a call.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said No. They haven’t called back since. Oh well…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
